<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anthropologie abstracted: or The idea of humane nature reflected in briefe philosophicall, and anatomicall collections.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 98 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1589_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873343</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170136</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170136)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 201:E1589[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anthropologie abstracted: or The idea of humane nature reflected in briefe philosophicall, and anatomicall collections.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 201 [i.e. 191], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman, at the Anchor in the lower walke in the New Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Final numbered page misnumbered 201.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August 30".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Physiology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Senses and sensation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anthropology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170136:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANTHROPOLOGIE</hi> ABSTRACTED: OR THE <hi>Idea of Humane Nature</hi> Reflected in briefe <hi>Philoſophicall, and Anatomicall</hi> COLLECTIONS.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <bibl>Iſaac-Caſaubon. in Elogio ſuo Audr. Laurentij Anatom.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> at the Anchor in the lower walke in the New Exchange. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:170136:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170136:2"/>
            <head>THE STATIONER TO THE READER, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ould Cuſtom have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed, I well might have preſented this diſcourſe to the World, without the Formality of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle: it being in it ſelf ſo rich and abſolute, as to deſerve a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and gratefull acceptance at the hands of all judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. But, ſince uſe hath made it a Law, that the Readers Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite muſt be excited by ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, conteining either ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of the <hi>Author,</hi> or a
<pb facs="tcp:170136:3"/>Summary account of the <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> treated of by him: it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns me to advertiſe you, (though briefly and plainly) of ſome things, the Knowledge whereof cannot but, in ſome meaſure, conduce both to your more eaſie <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of the <hi>Deſign</hi> of this <hi>Orphan piece;</hi> and the Juſtification of my <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Coſt,</hi> beſtowed upon the publiſhing of it.</p>
            <p>As for the Author, therefore, be pleaſed to know, that He was a Perſon ſo Eminent both for Wit and Learning, that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity wherein He was educated, and at length deſervedly honoured with the Degree of Doctor in Phyſick, eſteemed him as one of the moſt hopefull of his Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and one of the choiceſt Plants
<pb facs="tcp:170136:3"/>in all her Seminary; and when the haſty hand of Fate had crop: him in the Budd, lamented his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature Death, with Generall ſorrow, ſo that his Funerall Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor (as I have been lately told) was allowed to have ſpoken the genuine ſenſe of his Auditory, when he ſaid: <hi>Our loſſe is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than to be felt at once, 'tis Time, and the want of ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to ſucceed into his room, that onely can teach us the juſt proportion of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and his Worth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Book it ſelf; though both the Subject Matter, and Language are far above the ſphere of my mean judgement: yet I may adventure (and ſafely too, I preſume) to tell you from ſome others, even of the higheſt
<pb facs="tcp:170136:4"/>Form of Scholars, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Rudiments of that moſt excellent Knowledge, the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſelves;</hi> and thoſe too not onely diſpoſed into the moſt advantageous Method, as well for information, as Memory, but alſo clad in ſuch proper and ſelect Phraſes, as ſoften the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Notions, and in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry period, refreſh the Attention with variety of elegant Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. So that it is a queſtion (and long may continue ſo) whether <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> or <hi>Rhetorick</hi> can claim the greateſt ſhare in this <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>Author</hi> ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to Communicate it to the Publique, I could by no meanes learn: but the Exactneſse of the work may, in ſome ſort, warrant
<pb facs="tcp:170136:4"/>my Conjecture, that he wrote it not onely for his own uſe: it being not uſuall, for Learned men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſo much ſweat and oyle upon poliſhing and adorning their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Collections and Memorialls, as was neceſſary to make this ſo accurate. However, my good Fortune hath, after more than a dozen years ſince the Authors deceaſe, brought it into my hands; and I doubt not but the benefit you ſhall receive by the peruſing thereof, will fully convince you, that the Conſideration of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what beſide my own Gain, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon me to put the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yours. In the confidence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it becomes me to refer you to the Book it ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Herringman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170136:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170136:5"/>
            <head>OF THE NATURE OF THE <hi>HVMAN SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>NTHROPOLOGIE,</hi> or the Hiſtory of Human Nature, is, in the Vulgar (yet juſt) impreſſion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed into two Volumes; The firſt entituled <hi>Pſychologie,</hi> the nature of the Rationall Soule diſcourſed: the other <hi>Anatomie,</hi> the Fabrick or ſtructure of the body of man revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in diſſection. This we ſhall viſit only <hi>in tranſcurſu,</hi> and draw a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory Landſchip of ſo much only, as may preſent the method of the Soules <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> and her manner of diſpenſing orders to each diſtinct organ of the body: of the former, we ſhall in a diſtracted reherſall, deliver our Collections.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170136:6"/>
               <p>The <hi>Soule</hi> (called <hi>Anima,</hi> by all the Friends of wiſdome) is conſidered in a double ſenſe (1.) as <hi>Principium &amp; altera pars compoſiti, ſeu ut Forma corporis,</hi> the principall halfe of the compoſition, or the Forme of the body. (2.) as <hi>Efficiens operationum,</hi> the Efficient of all actions. Of the acception of the Soule in each of theſe reſpects, briefly; and firſt of the reaſonable Soule as it is <hi>related</hi> to the body.</p>
               <p>There is no one of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, whoſe judgement is in health, denies the <hi>reaſonable Soule</hi> to bee the <hi>Eſſentiall Forme</hi> of Man. But, ſince there is a double Forme (1.) one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Forma informans,</hi> which being the beginning, and nobler part of the compound, conſtitutes its ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fich <hi>Eſſence, and differenceth</hi> it from all other bodies. (2.) another, named <hi>Aſſistens,</hi> which doth not give to the thing <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to be a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick Eſſence; but to a thing alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy rich and perfect in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is <hi>ſuperadded</hi> as <hi>Acceſſary</hi> or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutant,</hi> to the performance of ſome nobler actions then of its ſelfe it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170136:6"/>could enterpriſe: in this ſence, is the <hi>Pilot</hi> ſaid to be the Eſſence or ſoul of the ſhip, although he contribute not to the ſhip its <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, its being, but as an Acceſſarie or Auxiliary joyned with the ſhip, is the Author or cauſe of its courſe and navigation, which the ſhip of its owne ſingle power cannot perform: here it wil be ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to enquire,<note place="margin">An Anima ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis ſit ejus forma infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans? an tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum aſſiſtens?</note> 
                  <hi>An Anima rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſit forma hominis informans, altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ejus pars? an verò tantum aſsiſtens, quae homini jam perfecto &amp; formam ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificam habenti adjungatur, &amp; nobilioris in eo operationis alicujus, puta intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, cauſa ſit?</hi> Whether the Rationall Soul be the Form informing &amp; one chief part of man; or only aſſiſtant, which to a man already complete in his own diſtinct eſſence, is adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and is the cauſe of ſome nobler operation <hi>(viz.)</hi> intelligence in him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Arabian Averrhoes would</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray our reaſon to an abſurdity, by his aſſertion, <hi>Formam hominis eſſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitativam, &amp;c.</hi> that the Eſſence of man is <hi>cogitative</hi> (a narrow terme, he is pleaſed to aſſigne it) and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170136:7"/>diſtinct from the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that by this, man did make a diſtinct ſpecies: but the Rationall Soule is onely the <hi>Aſſiſtant forme.</hi> To this error our faith ſtands no way affected. We ſhall declare for thoſe that adviſe us; that the rationall Soule is the true Eſſence of man, and the one and nobler morty of him.</p>
               <p>For,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> if the Reaſonable Soul were not the <hi>Forma informans</hi> of man, he could owne the attribute of rationall, with no leſſe abſurdity, then a ſhip can be allowed to be intelligent, onely becauſe it carries a Pilot that is ſo.</p>
               <p>Againe,</p>
               <p>That,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> whereby any thing does o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, is the <hi>Forme or Eſſence</hi> of that thing, to which we aſcribe the <hi>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> for nothing operates but by its Forme; But to man, (<hi>Quatenùs</hi> man) we attribute <hi>reaſon</hi> or <hi>intellecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Ergo, the rationall Soule is the <hi>Eſſentiall Forme</hi> of the body of man.</p>
               <p>It ſatisfies not, to converſion, that the Heretiques to this truth urge, that the underſtanding Faculty is accumulated to man <hi>per Phantaſmata;</hi> for theſe <hi>Phantaſmes</hi> have no nearer
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170136:7"/>a relation to the intellect, then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours to the ſight: and as colours, nor the ſubject on which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, can bee capable of ſight; ſo can neither the Phantaſmes, nor their ſubject underſtand, but are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed underſtood: Wherefore we may conclude thus.</p>
               <p>That,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> whereby one thing is <hi>in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> diſtinguiſhed from another, is its Eſſence; but man, by the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Soule, is diſtinguiſhed from all other living Creatures. Ergo, <hi>The rationall Soule is the Eſſence of Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this one foot of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> wee could add the other of <hi>Authority,</hi> to make this opinion current: but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panſion, in contraction is a <hi>Paradoxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The explication of this,<note place="margin">An Anima ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionalis in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus hominibus ſit una? an verò in ſingulis peculiaris?</note> uſhers our reaſon to the ſolution of a ſecond queſtion, viz. <hi>An Anima rationalis in omnibus hominibus ſit una numero; an verò in ſingulis peculiaris?</hi> whether there be but one numericall Soule in all mankind; or whether a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct one in every individuall?</p>
               <p>They that determine the reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Soule to bee but <hi>Forma aſsiſtens,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170136:8"/>dreame that it is not multiplied ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of men, but that there is but one ſingle Soule in all the Species, which is the cauſe of intelligence in men. This is, <hi>è diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro,</hi> in oppoſition to truth, many waies. For, every <hi>Forma informans,</hi> (ſuch as we have already acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al Soul to be) is mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed, as the individualls are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed. (2.) If we allow but one Soul to all men, it will be conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that all men are but one man, for they would have but one and the ſame numericall Forme. (3.) The <hi>Operations, and intellections or ſecond acts</hi> are multiplyed according to the number of individualls, for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence is diſtinct from the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of another. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Soule, which is the <hi>firſt act,</hi> is multiplyed: For the diverſity of <hi>operations</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the diverſity of <hi>Formes:</hi> (4.) In one and the ſame intellect, would be at the ſame inſtant, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinions; for one man harbours one opinion, a ſecond another, a third a quite contrary to both. But we ſhould ſupererogate to light a candle to the Sunne.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170136:8"/>
               <p>From this poſition, that the Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Soule is the true forme of man, a ſecond Quere receives a hint to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate it ſelfe, <hi>viz. An eadem ſit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalis?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An Anima ſit immortalis?</note> 
                  <hi>ſeu, an poſsit ſine ſui interitu à corpore ſeparari?</hi> Whether this Soule be immortall, or whether it can bee divorced from the body, without the deſtruction of its Eſſence? For us Chriſtians, it is the eaſie buſineſſe of our <hi>Faith,</hi> grounded on the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of our Religion, to atteſt that the Soule is immortall, and that the excellency of it, is filed among thoſe grand maximes, on which, as hinges, Chriſtianity is moved. But whether it be not an object too ſubtile and ſublime, for reaſon, though clarified by the bright perſpective of <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,</hi> to diſcerne, is an argument yet full of perplexity and trouble.</p>
               <p>Firſt, let us with <hi>J.C. Scaliger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Scaliger Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercit. <hi>61.</hi> ſect. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; Excercit. <hi>307.</hi> ſect. <hi>20.</hi> Solus Deus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rè immortalis &amp; incorruptibilis, quia ſolus ex ſe ſuum eſſe habet, atque à nullo dependit; Dei verò reſpectu oinnia creata mortalia &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptibilia ſunt, quae à Creatoris nutu deponi poſſunt ab ea eſſentia, in qua conſtituta ſunt. Non corrumpuntur tamen quaedam ut Angeli, &amp; Anima rationalis, quia Creator non vult ea Corrumpi, &amp; nihil contrarii ipſis, à quo corrumpuntur, condidit, nec eas ita materiae immerſit, ut extra eam nec ſubſiſtere, nec operari poſſint.</note> grant that <hi>God</hi> alone is truely <hi>immortall and incorruptible;</hi> and inferr, that there is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170136:9"/>one immortall, which is ſuperior to to decay, or ruine, and being abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſimple in its owne nature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives being from its ſelfe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends not on any ſecond: and ſuch is <hi>God</hi> only, and in reſpect of him all things may be ſaid ſubject to change by <hi>Corruption.</hi> For although <hi>Angells</hi> and the <hi>rationall Soule,</hi> which are in a third ſence, allowed immortall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are never actually cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, conſiſt of no contraries, and are abſolutely ſingle in their Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>à ſubjecto:</hi> yet becauſe they are not abſolute, <hi>à Cauſa,</hi> have not their <hi>Eſſe</hi> from themſelves, but derive it from another, by which they may be returned to <hi>Non-entities</hi> againe. For every <hi>dependant</hi> is lyable, at the arbitrary reſolve of that, on which it doth depend, to be changed; and may at the pleaſure of its <hi>principle,</hi> be depoſed from that Eſſence, in which it was, by it, created.</p>
               <p>But the reaſon why ſome created natures are not corrupted, is the <hi>will and decree</hi> of the <hi>Creator;</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted them ſingle and ſimple without the mixture of a contrary,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170136:9"/>(from which they might derive corruptibility) nor ſo obliged them to matter, as that they cannot <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt,</hi> or <hi>operate</hi> without it. And that amongſt natures of this order, the rational ſoul of man is to be liſted; and that it may be ſevered from the body, without the ruine of its eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, is the task of the wiſer and modern Philoſopher to prove. <hi>vid. Marſil. Ficin. de immortalit. Animae. Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Tolet. de Anim. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Quaest.</hi> 16. <hi>Fran. Picol. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Hum. ment. Colleg. Conimbr. in Tract. de Anim. Separat. diſput.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſtate of all which buſineſſe is briefly thus.</p>
               <p>Every thing is known by its <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,</hi> and every form reveals it ſelfe by its <hi>operations;</hi> wherefore ſince the actions of man are ſo <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> that they cannot be attributed to a mortal ſubſtance, deeply plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in matter; it may without ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity be collected, that the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſoul, from which theſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent and divine actions flow, is <hi>immortal</hi> and <hi>ſeparable</hi> from matter.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>intellect</hi> does <hi>abſtract</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170136:10"/>deveſt things of that <hi>matter,</hi> judgeth of them without the conditions of <hi>matter, quantity,</hi> or <hi>figure,</hi> contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plates them as unbodied and enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the groſſer bondage of their materials; is not (as the frailer ſenſe) offended, either with the <hi>multitude,</hi> or <hi>vehemence</hi> of objects, but can comprehend things infinite in number, yet ſtil reſerves room for more, &amp; can multiply their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to a higher finity, reflects on its ſelf, and is familiar with, not only others, but its own nature, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands that it doth underſtand its own intelligence; can <hi>decree,</hi> and <hi>repeal,</hi> and <hi>reſolve,</hi> and labour with an inſatiable deſire of <hi>knowledg, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Beatitude,</hi> (which ſince it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of ſatisfaction in this life, we have reaſon to believe, that there is reſerved for it a future e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, in which this appetite ſhal be ſated) and can perform its actions without the inſtruments or organs of the body.</p>
               <p>This of the Soul in her relation to the body.</p>
               <p>The diſquiſition of its nature, as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170136:10"/>it is <hi>principium operationum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anima immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta <hi>1.</hi> ab. objecto.</note> the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of all actions ſucceeds. To the deſcription of it in this ſence, the words of <hi>Ariſtotle, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de anima. Anima rationalis eſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>immiſta,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach very near. But the ſoul muſt be granted ſimple, pure, immateri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and unmixt, in a double reſpect. (1.) <hi>ab objectis,</hi> that its eſſence might not participate with the eſſence of objects, but be indued only with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power to receive them. For, ſince the buſineſſe of the ſoul is the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion,</hi> and <hi>knowledg</hi> of objects; and this can beperformed only by <hi>reception;</hi> it is a neceſſary illation, that its eſſence muſt be <hi>ſimple, pure, and unmixt</hi> with the eſſence of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. For, nothing, without an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to reaſon, can be ſaid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that, which is its own already by eſſence: <hi>&amp; intus existens prohibet alienum.</hi> And this <hi>immiſtion</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the rational ſoul with the <hi>ſenſes</hi> alſo: For, they in like manner contain not their objects in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but have only a <hi>Capacity</hi> of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving</hi> them in: but here's the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the ſenſes are free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170136:11"/>only <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> and from one ſingle <hi>ſpecies</hi> of <hi>Ens</hi> (for example, the <hi>Sight</hi> is free only from <hi>Colours</hi>) for their buſineſſe is not about a plurality of Entities; but the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſoul is abſolutely free from eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of all other things, as, being by the inſtitution of God, directed to the <hi>reception</hi> and <hi>admiſſion</hi> of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Natures.</p>
               <p>Again,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Immiſta ab Organo.</note> the fational ſoul is by a peculiar manner <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>immiſta ab or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gano, nec cum eqpermiſta.</hi> Free, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>organical, when it operats in acts <hi>intelligential,</hi> or <hi>voluntary,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms its actions without the bodies aſſiſtance. For ſince to the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe actions which are done in and by the body, there is a peculiar, harmonious temper of qualities, (for every particular reception ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects a diſtinct, exact preparation, and diſpoſition) and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, an equally tempered Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan of the ſame conſtitution, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and ſince each diſtinct part of the human body, hath a proper and diſtinct temper: but the rational ſoul is neither (as it is in it ſelfe)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170136:11"/>obliged to any certain definite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, or compoſition of firſt qualities; nor affected by them: nor can there in the body be found any adaequate and proper Organ for it: we muſt confeſſe, that the ſoul in the diſpatch of her buſineſſe hath no dependance on the body, but is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material,</hi> and <hi>inorganical.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this third immiſſion of the ſoul, we have a cleer proſpect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her <hi>operations.</hi> For ſince ſhe in <hi>Agendo</hi> is not obliged to the body, and that the actions of the body communicate nothing with the actions of the mind: it reſults a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar truth, that the <hi>underſtanding</hi> and <hi>will,</hi> are <hi>powers inorganical,</hi> and do <hi>Agere</hi> of themſelves; ſo that to <hi>underſtand</hi> and to <hi>will,</hi> are the <hi>proper actions</hi> of the <hi>mind;</hi> nor doth the mind underſtand by the body, or any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of it, as by a <hi>Medium</hi> neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               <p>Indeed ſhe is beholding to the <hi>Imagination,</hi> for while ſhe remaines immured in this darke Monaſtery, the body, ſhee never underſtands without the aſſiſtance of the Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170136:12"/>
                  <hi>(Ariſtot. Lib. 3. de Anima. cap. 7.)</hi> yet not as <hi>Organon,</hi> but as <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectum.</hi> For it is neceſſary that intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligibles be conveyed to the <hi>reaſon</hi> by the <hi>ſenſe.</hi> Wherefore, if any ſhall poſitively aſſert, that the actions of the minde are Organicall; and that the Rationall Soule doth make uſe of the ſubſervient miniſtry of the <hi>Braine</hi> and <hi>Animal ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>ſenſes,</hi> as her <hi>Corporeall inſtruments:</hi> We dare admit it, onely in the ſubſequent ſence. That the Soule, while ſhee ſojournes in the reſult of duſt and aſhes, doth not underſtand, without the operations of the Organs of the body praeceding her owne operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: or that in her ſecond and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate actions ſhe becomes inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall,<note place="margin">Hinc ſagaciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Romani Imperij reip. sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icae, &amp; ſui ipſius <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Mare. Ant. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> Exclamat, Ah! quando veniet illud tempus ô anima, cum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, ſimplex, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica, &amp; nuda, corpore denique tibi circumjecto, magis conſpicua eris, cum gustabis perfecti amoris affectum: plend eris, nullius indigens, nibil defiderans, neque animati, neque inanimati ad fruitiones velupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c. l. <hi>1.</hi> n. <hi>10.</hi> Ex verſione Merie. Caſaubon.</note> and uſes the aſſiſtance of the Braine and Animall Spirits: but not in the leaſt meaſure, when ſhee operates <hi>perſe,</hi> and is undiſturbedly imploy'd about her pure <hi>intelligence, and pure will:</hi> for then her ſublimer conceptions and intellection tower
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170136:12"/>in an immaterial Sphere, ſuperior to that wherein the duller medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Organs confines her, and is her ſelf the ſubject of her owne ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, and intelligence and will. Which laſt act is by a new, yet convenient notion, called <hi>Volition Scaliger. Exercit.</hi> 307. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>And although the underſtanding Faculty doth ſuffer depravation in diſeaſes of the braine: yet that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on no other reaſon, then that the ſubordinate, and ſubminiſtring Faculties, which are Organicall and intereſſed in the Conſtitution of the braine, are injured.</p>
               <p>Moreover, though the Human Soule be plentifully furniſhed with all the Attributes of the Vegetative and ſenſible Soule: yet ſhe is enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with two other diviner Faculties, (whereby ſhe tranſcends in excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all other vegetable and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive creatures)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Intellectus.</note> the <hi>Intellect,</hi> whereby wee conceive and know; (2.) the <hi>will,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Voluntas.</note> which inclines us to thoſe things, which in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our reaſon are good. The ſence of this dictated to <hi>Hermes Triſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megiſtus,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170136:13"/>this ſentence; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <hi>Homo brutis &amp; mundo praeſtat rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; mente.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The difference of theſe two facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiesis manifeſt, for it is one thing to <hi>know,</hi> and another to <hi>deſire</hi> the things known. Further, theſe two operate diverſly; the fourmer, <hi>Patiendo,</hi> and by <hi>admiſſion</hi> of the ſpecies, ſo that they may be intromitted to the mind; the latter <hi>Agendo,</hi> and by <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> ſo that the mind may be by extramiſſion, advanced towards the object. Again, the diverfity of their objects diſcerns the power of <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> from the power of <hi>Volition:</hi> for, we know things <hi>quatenus entia,</hi> but we deſire them <hi>quatenus bona.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This, by ſtrong inference makes good, that the intellect is not ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with, yet hath a power ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to admit and comprehend all other <hi>actual Entities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> poſſeſſed with an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, that in the mind of man, beſide that which hath a power to be made, all things, <hi>viz.</hi> by intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and ſupplies the place of <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170136:13"/>there is alſo ſomething elſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging the office of <hi>Form,</hi> which hath power to make all things, <hi>viz.</hi> actually intelligible: differenceth the intellect into (1) <hi>Active,</hi> and (2) <hi>Paſsive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to determine what this <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus Agens</hi> is, hath afflicted the braines of firmer heads then ours. Some (&amp; thoſe of the upper houſe of <hi>Philoſophers</hi>) have voted it to be the Supreame wiſdome, or ſome Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or Superior intelligence auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant to man. But theſe dreamers rove as wide off the ſence of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> as of Truth. For his theame in <hi>Lib. de Anima</hi> is <hi>Intellectus Humanus:</hi> and in <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de An. c.</hi> 5. he expreſsly calls the <hi>Active Intelligence,</hi> a certaine <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> in the Soule. (2.) Againe, this <hi>intellection,</hi> which ſtreams from the <hi>Active intellect,</hi> is ſetled within the region of our ſelves, and under our own command, and is not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted immediately from God, or any other auxiliary intelligence (3.). Laſtly, ſince God in the fabrick <hi>of our intellect,</hi> hath inriched it with a wealthy meaſure of illumination;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170136:14"/>we ſhall blaſpheme the bounty and wiſedome of our Creation, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell him to bee immediately ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor and aſſiſtant to it in all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But the <hi>Active intellect</hi> is in the ſence of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Intellectus Agens.</note> that difference of our <hi>informator, our Soule,</hi> which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth things <hi>intelligible in poteſtate to the perfection of intelligibles in Actu.</hi> For as an effect <hi>Naturall</hi> owes its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to an <hi>Agent</hi> of the ſame <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> and to Effects <hi>Artificiall</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a diſtinct <hi>Art:</hi> ſo to the worke of the mind, which is the act of intelligence is required an <hi>Agent,</hi> not Heterogeneous, ſeveral and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from, but what is a part or certaine difference of the Soul.</p>
               <p>And although this <hi>Intellectus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens</hi> be, by the ſeverity of ſome judgments, proclaimed an exile from the borders of Philoſophy: yet that it will become the juſtice of our reaſon to welcome it, is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable from this truth. Whatſoever action is done, is performed <hi>in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo, et abl aliquo, ſedalio,</hi> in, and by ſome ſecond that is different: Now univerſals are made, the intellect
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170136:14"/>being <hi>Paſsive: Ergo,</hi> there muſt be ſome other <hi>active</hi> power to make univerſals. For ſince every patient requires a determinate Agent, and nothing in nature can deduce it ſelf, <hi>è poteſtate in actum:</hi> and ſince our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is conſtituted only in the power, or capacity to admit objects actually intelligible, and that by reception: it follows, that if we allow a Paſſive, we cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an Active intellect; and if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move one, we loſe both. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an <hi>intellectus agens</hi> is neceſſary for this reaſon, that it may make all things actually intelligible, and tranſlate the object <hi>de ordine in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> from the capacity to the act. For ſince every object or phantaſm is material, and ſo under the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite condition of the power intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, which is abſtracted, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material, it cannot be comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the intellect, until it become abſtracted, immaterial, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate to the intellect; and this can never be done, but by a <hi>power abſtracted,</hi> and an <hi>eſſence intelligent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this we may derive infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170136:15"/>that the <hi>Office</hi> of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is <hi>Agere (i.e.)</hi> to advance from the <hi>Capacity</hi> to the <hi>act;</hi> and of objects intelligible in <hi>Potentia,</hi> to make them intelligible in <hi>actu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This office of the underſtanding the Philoſopher explains by that analogy or ſimilitude, which it holds with <hi>Art, Nature, Habit,</hi> and <hi>Light.</hi> For it is as it were the <hi>eye</hi> of the minde, and is as neerly related to objects, as Light to Colours. It ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyes and illuſtrats the phantaſmes or objects, naked and deveſted of thoſe material conditions, which like clouds, benight their intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibility, that they may be reinve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the brighter nature of intelligibles; and thus like prepared Brides be preſented to the embraces of the Paſſive intellect: juſt as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours tranſmit their image to the ſight by the <hi>qualification</hi> and <hi>aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of <hi>light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this illuſtration, illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or qualification of the Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſmes, is not done <hi>Formaliter,</hi> ſo that they retain the impreſſion of any quality, nor <hi>objectivè</hi> only, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170136:15"/>
                  <hi>effectivé;</hi> becauſe the active intellect as an external <hi>light,</hi> doth by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation of its own luſtre, ſublime the objects to the production of the image intelligible: Neither is the <hi>in ellectus agens</hi> required only <hi>pro ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto,</hi> for a ſubject, but hath an other part to act, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Paſſive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect, to produce the act of intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, by repreſenting to it, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in its intelligible ſpecies: and this it performes, when aſſociated with the illumined object, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the image of the intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the paſſive intellect. Hence may we collect, (1.) on what, (2.) in what manner the Active intellect does <hi>operate;</hi> for it is required to the performance of both actions, as wel that it operats on the objects, as on the Paſſive intellect; but on each in a diſtince and ſeveral manner: for it is joyned to the phantaſmes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the act of intelligence; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, while they are yet remaining in the imagination, where illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating them, it becomes their <hi>Form,</hi> whereby they are conſtituted the <hi>Objectum motivum</hi> of the Paſſive
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170136:16"/>intellect: after joyned in commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with theſe objects thus illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, it operats on the paſſive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect, by producing in it the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies intelligible; and by ſequel, the <hi>intellection</hi> or act of underſtanding.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>intellectus agens</hi> doth not underſtand, <hi>quà Agens,</hi> ſince it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives not the images or notions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, although it <hi>produce</hi> them; neither is fited in the capacity of intelligence, but is the intellection in the Paſſive intellect, as in its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, wherefore this is called <hi>intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus Formaliter;</hi> the other only <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctivè,</hi> becauſe it effects the intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>The intellectus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Paſsive,</hi> is,<note place="margin">Iutellectus patibilis.</note> as it were the <hi>matter,</hi> or <hi>ſubject,</hi> on which the images intelligible are impreſſed. Hence it derives the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of <hi>Patient</hi> and <hi>Patible,</hi> for it is paſſive in the admiſſion of the ſpecies, by the intervention, or mediation of the Phantaſms. This is alſo called <hi>intellectus poſsibilis, et mens pote state;</hi> becauſe it is endued with a capacity to be all things by intelligence. But to reveal the dark
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170136:16"/>and myſterious ſence of theſe words, <hi>the underſtanding paſsive hath a capacity to be made all things by intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,</hi> we muſt be illuminated by a beam of that refnlgent Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Firmament of Learning. <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Jul. Caeſ. Scaliger Exercit.</hi> 307. Sect. 6. <hi>Principio (inquit) nego tibi illud â Philoſopho dictum eſſe; intellectum noſtrum eſſe omnia eſſentialiter, aut formaliter: Sed eſt omnia ſubjectivè, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut Materia prima: quae non fit Equi eſſentia ſuh equi forma, ſed remanet id, quod erat ſubſtantia quaedam: ex qua &amp; forma, fit hoc aliquid. Alia tamenratio eſt in intellectus informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one. Ipſe enìm non eſt potentia pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, ut materia prima, quae reducatur ad hoc, ut actu ſit hee aliquid per for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam. Sed ipſe forma noſtra eſt ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialis, ſeparabilis, incorruptibilis, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternus, ex quo tanquam ex ſubjecto eſſentialiter perfecto, &amp; ſpecie, quam recipit fit intellectus informatus: non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias a ſeipſo: niſi ſicut Caeſar edoctus, fit alius à ſeipſo: propter receptas ſpecies accide ntales. Nonigitur fit intellectus ſimpliciter, nec fit ipſa ſpecies, ſed ſub ſpecie.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170136:17"/>
               <p>The reflex of all which is, that the intellect Paſſive, is not capable of being all things <hi>Eſſentially,</hi> but <hi>Subjectively.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As in this, which concernes the firſt difference of the underſtanding, we have exerciſed the <hi>patience:</hi> ſo we ſhall the <hi>mercy</hi> of <hi>Candor,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume forgiveneſſe if we adde: that the intellect Active and Paſſive are hot <hi>Eſſentially and Really,</hi> but onely in the <hi>reaſon diſtinct.</hi> For, two internall Formes cannot be united by new ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents: and both to effect, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an Action <hi>immanent</hi> (ſuch as is the intellection) is required a principle <hi>ſingle</hi> in Eſſence. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our ſenſe is, that the Eſſence of the Active and Paſſive intellect, is one &amp; the ſame: and that <hi>quoad Eſse,</hi> there is but one intellect; which, in that it makes things intelligible, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrates the Phantaſmes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt's them to the cuſtody of the Paſſive, is called the Agent: but in that it is the <hi>Subject Recipient</hi> of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted and immateriall objects, it deſervedly ownes the name of <hi>Paſſive.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170136:17"/>
               <p>In this ſeamleſſe Veſture, the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> the factious ſpeculation of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Inellectus in</note> would eſpie a ſecond rent; and untwiſt it into an intellect (1. in <hi>Hahit,</hi> and (2.) in <hi>Act:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Habitu. <hi>2.</hi> Actu.</note> but Truth dictares, that theſe are onely the <hi>degrees</hi> of one, and the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect: and are not by any Law, but that arbitrary power of diſcourſe, warranted for <hi>differences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, that is the intellect in <hi>Habit,</hi> which hath the object treaſured up in the wealthy Magazine of the Phanſy; and by one degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection tranſcends the intellect in poſſibility. For this is in the capacity to the <hi>firſt</hi> Act; but that for the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,</hi> or, is prepared to admit the action of the <hi>Agent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning this <hi>Zabarell</hi> hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoughts; and believes, that the mind of man is at firſt <hi>rude, fallow</hi> and <hi>unapt</hi> to the knowledge &amp; compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of intelligibles: but after, by the <hi>acts of intelligence multiplyed,</hi> it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſo large an <hi>hability</hi> and <hi>aptitude</hi> to comprehenſion: that it can, without labour and difficulty, at its own pleaſure, addreſſe it ſelf to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170136:18"/>
                  <hi>imagination,</hi> and immediately un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand: and that the intellect en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with this faire Hability, is called the <hi>Intellect in Habit:</hi> but when the Paſſive intellect doth actually operate <hi>(i. e.)</hi> actually diſcern the object preſented, it is called the <hi>Intellect in Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt diſtinction of the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect is into (1.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Intellectus. <hi>1.</hi> Speculations. <hi>2.</hi> Practicus.</note> 
                  <hi>Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum, &amp;</hi> (2.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Practicum.</hi> Which termes doe not conſtitute a <hi>duality</hi> of powers intellectuall, nor inſinuate, either the <hi>differences</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of the ſame intellect: but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly expreſſe both Faculties of the rationall Soul: by the Epithite <hi>Speculativum;</hi> the <hi>Underſtanding</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called; by <hi>practicum</hi> the <hi>Will.</hi> For when the intellect, in regard of its <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a thing; and again, according to the affirmation or nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the true or falſe, cannnot be expreſſed by any more convenient name then <hi>Speculative:</hi> it followes, that this difference aroſe in reſpect of the third attribute of the intellect practicall, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>proſecution</hi> and <hi>averſion</hi> or <hi>flight,</hi> which are <hi>acts</hi> of the <hi>Will.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170136:18"/>
               <p>The <hi>Operation</hi> of the intellect (to which all the offices of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees are deſtined) is <hi>Intellection.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Intellectus ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio.</note> Which is not the ſame with the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages intelligible, but really differs from them; and is more truly defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (1.) by the <hi>reception</hi> and <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Simplex. <hi>2.</hi> Compoſita.</note> (2.) by the <hi>judgement</hi> of the ſpecies intelligible. For the intellect exerciſeth a double operation on the object; the firſt a <hi>ſimple</hi> or bare apprehenſion or Knowledge: the ſecond (called Compoſition and Diviſion) a <hi>compound</hi> apprehenſion or judgement, which conſiſts in the <hi>aſſent</hi> or <hi>diſſent.</hi> Henceis the intellect ſaid to be double alſo (1.) <hi>ſimple,</hi> when it knows an object ſimple and incomplex. (2.) <hi>Compound,</hi> when it judgeth a propoſition true, or falſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The objectof intellection,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ojectum intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectionis Ens.</note> which both moves, and determines the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, is <hi>Ens,</hi> accepted univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, and as it comprehends both <hi>materiall</hi> and <hi>immateriall natures;</hi> yet allayed with ſome neceſſary quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications and conditions: and firſt <hi>Univerſality;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſate.</note> for that <hi>Ens</hi> may be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170136:19"/>received and diſcerned by the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Intelligibile.</note> it muſt be abſtracted and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from ſingulars: (2.) <hi>intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> or ſublimation from the faecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent condition of matter: (3.) <hi>verity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Verum.</note> This object, thus, by the Active intellect adaequated, condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionated, and proportioned to the mind, is called <hi>ſpicies intelligibilis,</hi> the <hi>image intelligible:</hi> as that which the courſer ſenſe receives, is called <hi>ſpecies ſenſibilis,</hi> the <hi>image ſenſible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe intelligible Species are the <hi>Phantaſms</hi> illumined,<note place="margin">Phantaſmata illuminata, quid.</note> irradiated, illuſtrated <hi>(i.e.)</hi> extracted from the dreggs or conditions of matter, and by the Active impreſſed on the paſſive intellect; and by the rule of Conſequence, are <hi>Accidents ſpirituall and indiviſible.</hi> For not the ſubſtance, but the accidents, find admiſſion to the ſenſe. <hi>Scalig. Exercit.</hi> 303. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. Wherefore onely accidents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the Species in the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Among theſe are <hi>Locus, Tempus, &amp; unitas finita quantitatis;</hi> which being removed by the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power of the intellect, there will reſide the <hi>ſubſtantiall univerſall</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170136:19"/>Species: as when you ſee any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed or armed, firſt you diſcerne the armes; when they are ſublated, the man himſelf.</p>
               <p>To relieve our aſſertion (that the things which are to become objects to the intellect, muſt be ſtript,<note place="margin">Mens humana ſingularia cognoſcit.</note> and diſroabed of matter and Conditions ſingular) from the ambuſh of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; it will be opportune to reſolve; after what manner the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding can know <hi>ſingulars;</hi> or whether it be capable onely of <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalls?</hi> Our determination is, that the mind of man doth alſo compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend ſingulars. For ſince all the ſubordinate <hi>cognoſcent</hi> Faculties are ſo, by mutuall concatenation uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and as it were identified, that the end of one action is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to another; and whatever is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by an inferior, is alſo famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to a ſuperior Faculty: but the ſenſe and imagination comprehend <hi>ſingulars:</hi> wherefore, by neceſſary inference, the mind knowes <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> alſo. And from this knowledge, is man enabled to compare and ballance an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall</hi> with a <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar;</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170136:20"/>and the mind formes ſingular propoſitions, that from them, it may collect <hi>Univerſalls:</hi> and ſo often corrects the ſenſes judgement of ſingulars, as they, by reaſon of their diſaffection or depraved diſpoſition to the objects, are guilty of deluſion &amp; aberration. But this cognition of fingulars is wrought by Accidents; for from proper ſingular accidents, we extract the notion proper to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars; as in like manner, from the notions proper to the ſpecies, wee pick out the Phantaſme proper to the ſpecies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Intellection,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Intellectio.</note> or the Act of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is vulgarly diſunioned into (1.) <hi>Rectam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Recta. <hi>2.</hi> Reflexa.</note> direct or ſimple. (2.) <hi>Reflexam,</hi> reflex, or ingeminated. Our intellection is direct, when at the firſt limple apprehenſion, the Species arreſts and wholy poſſeſſes the intellect, ſo that it deſiſts from any further proſecution, or diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: as when it is barely imployed in the firſt conception of a man, Ox, or Horſe, &amp;c. <hi>Reflex.</hi> doubled, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocated, when the minde reflects on the knowledge of its ſelfe, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170136:20"/>doth underſtand its owne intellecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and diſcernes it ſelfe to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect; that is an Eſſence pure and immateriall, a bright nature, irradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by the reflexive glory of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Wiſedome.</p>
               <p>Here our Averſion to obſcurity may excuſe a ſhort digreſſion,<note place="margin">Abſtractio quid?</note> if we inſert, that, by <hi>Abſtraction</hi> we intend, a ſeparation of ſingling (in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding) out of one thiug from all others. For in abſtraction, not all things inherent in the ſubject are knowne, but onely that which is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted. <hi>V. G.</hi> to abſtract <hi>Animal ab Equo,</hi> the living Creature from the Horſe; is to conſider onely the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, the Equiety being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incouſidered and ſuperſeded.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>Voluntas the will,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Voluntas.</note> is the other power of the rationall Soul, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we <hi>proſecute</hi> or <hi>abhor, embrace,</hi> or <hi>reject</hi> the objects known by the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſanding: Or, is the <hi>intellect expan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; diffuſed, to admit, or execute</hi> what it underſtands. This alſo by ſome, is termed <hi>Appetitus Rationalis, the reaſonable appetite.</hi> For as the <hi>ſenſitive appetite</hi> followes the Knowledge
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170136:21"/>of the <hi>Senſe.</hi> So doth a proper and peculiar deſire of fruition attend the knowledge of the mind; which, for diſtinction from the former, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the appellation of the <hi>Will:</hi> and that the <hi>rationall</hi> doth abſolutely differ from the <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive</hi> appetite, is familiar from this,<note place="margin">Videatur Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij Prude ntij <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſeu de Compug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n tia Animae, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note> that they have too frequent Conflicts and Contentions betwixt them. This <hi>Antipathy</hi> or <hi>Duello</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two <hi>indigenae,</hi> the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous frailty of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> diſcovered to be radicated, beyond all poſſibility of reconcilement, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till our Exaltation from the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſenſuality; therefore with <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ejaculates his Vote for Emancipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the tyranny of Fleſh. And were this Philoſophy lectured to the Junior Phariſees of our Age, (though, would Charity diſpence, wee may fear their incapacity of Fixation, but by ignition, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, but by diſtillation <hi>per de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſum</hi>) it would deride their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of ſingular and divine purity; and humble them to confeſſion of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170136:21"/>their large ſympathicall diſtemper from the Common wounds of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity. But we ask pardon for our Parentheſis.</p>
               <p>The object,<note place="margin">Ejus Objectum. Bonum &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note> which provokes the will, is <hi>Bonum &amp; Malum, Good and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill;</hi> ſo conceived by the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and tendred to the will: hence it proſecutes good and abhors evill. The Actions of the will are (1.) <hi>Volition,</hi> (2.) <hi>Nolition;</hi> and theſe are double, (1.) <hi>Elicitae</hi> cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen or elected, which the will, by it ſelfe, and not by the inſervient Faculties, doth ſelect and execute: (2.) <hi>imperatae injunctive</hi> which the Will commands to bee done by the ſubordinate powers.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>ſubſervient Faculties,</hi> which by the Law of Fate, are ſubjects to the Scepter of the Will, are (1.) the <hi>Locomotive,</hi> (2.) the <hi>Senſitive Appetite.</hi> For our <hi>motion</hi> and <hi>quieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> ſucceed each other at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and command of the Will: But that <hi>dominon,</hi> which the Will, before our Grandfathers <hi>apoſtaſy</hi> from the rule of reaſon, extended over the <hi>ſenſuall Appetite,</hi> is contracted and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170136:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170136:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170136:23"/>diminiſhed by the uſurped in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment of <hi>Senſuality:</hi> and that harmonious concord, which at the primitive conſtitution, was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained betwixt both faculties, ſo confuſedly infringed; that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted <hi>ſenſitive Appetite,</hi> renounces all conformity to the ſober <hi>adviſo'es</hi> of the rationall Will: and may, with an eaſie Metaphor, aſſimilate <hi>Ovids, Fertur equis Auriga, nec audit Currus habenas:</hi> or that diviner diſtich of <hi>Hermanus. Hugo Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de piis Votis.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Frena nihil patitur minùs, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> libido vovendi,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nec ſe lege ſinunt libera vota premi.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There's naught abhorrs Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment like our luſt,</l>
                     <l>Nor are our Votes Conformed to what's juſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>But to a <hi>Lordſhip</hi> over the <hi>Vegetive Faculty,</hi> the Charter of the <hi>Will</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not: for that workes poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and abſolutely naturall, neither is our <hi>Nutrition, Accretion,</hi> or <hi>majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> at the improvement or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation</hi> of the <hi>Will.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170136:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Traduction of the Human Soul.</head>
               <p>THE ſecond grand Remora's, which retard the Soul, in her voyage for the diſcovery of <hi>wiſdom,</hi> and Charme her Compaſſe to a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation from the pacifick Sea of <hi>Truth,</hi> to the dangerous Torrent of <hi>Error;</hi> are (1.) <hi>ſervile Credulity</hi> (2.) <hi>Vainglorious Singularity.</hi> To the firſt, moſt have cowardly, or ſupinely, proſtituted their habilities of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition; and have ſo firmly vowed implicite homage to the ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraignty of Antiquity, that, if but a <hi>Tradition</hi> be contradicted, it proves Criminall, and <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> (the two beſt Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors) are depoſed as <hi>innovators.</hi> The other inveigles her diſciples into the oppoſite extream: and would demoliſh the ſubſtantial buildings, on which the reverend hand of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> hath recorded Truth, in deep ingravements: that on their ruines, the pageant ſuperſtructures of <hi>ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170136:24"/>dreams</hi> may find advancement. From this we may (we hope with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Treaſon againſt the Majeſty of juſtice) affirm our endeavours di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from the former, we deſpair not to relieve our <hi>Reader,</hi> who noe ſooner, with but halfe an eye, glances on the inſcription of this leafe; but preſumes our diſcouſe <hi>Erroneous,</hi> becauſe <hi>inquiſitive</hi> into the Antient and popular aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Human <hi>Soul is created by inſuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any ſhall here arreſt us, for an incroachment on the ſacred <hi>royalty of Theology;</hi> our <hi>plea</hi> is, that whatſoever of the Human Soules Originall is within the borders of reaſon, lyes in Common alſo to <hi>Philoſophy:</hi> that our thoughts are ſo clear from deſign to propagate <hi>Haereſie,</hi> or oppoſe our Conceptions to any <hi>Fundametnall</hi> of Faith: that we humbly tender them as <hi>Poſitions</hi> moſt probable and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneous to Verity; but not <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude</hi> them as <hi>Magiſteriall dictates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our firſt Article is; that the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſoul is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Theſis.</note> by the hereditary ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the divine benediction, <hi>Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170136:24"/>&amp; multiplicamini,</hi> propagated and traduced, by the ſee of Parents to their iſſue.</p>
               <p>Our firſt Argument hopes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment from that <hi>Axiome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument <hi>1.</hi> Simile, Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le generat.</note> 
                  <hi>Simile Simile generat,</hi> ſo appoſitely atteſted by <hi>Ariſtotle. Lib. de An. c.</hi> 4. <hi>T.</hi> 34: in theſe words: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. rehearſed thus: This operation, of all other, is moſt naturall to Animals, thoſe, I mean, which are perfect, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective or mutilated, and are not generated without ſeed; for every one to procreate his like, an Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, an Animal, a Plant, a Plant: That by this way, as far as they are able, they may enterpriſe perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity. For when the wiſe Creator conſtituted every thing, in its kind, perfect, but man, as his <hi>maſterpiece and abridgement</hi> (in whom the idae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a's of all other created natures are collectively refulgent) moſt <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>exact:</hi> he cannot juſtly owne the attribute of perfection, but muſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170136:25"/>be enrolled amongſt <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Mutilates,</hi> if he be deſtitute of power to procreate another man, perfect and altogether ſuch as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. This hath prevailed upon moſt Naturaliſts &amp; many Divines, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; That man does abſolutely procreate man and the whole man, which could not be, if the <hi>procreator</hi> did not communicate the Soul to his iſſue, for ſince man conſiſts of a body and a Soul, if the Soul be not communicative from the Genitors, man cannot propagate man.</p>
               <p>This alſo is conſentaneous, to the ſence of <hi>ſacred Scripture; For God</hi> (<hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 28.) diſtributed to man equally, with all other living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, his virtual benediction of <hi>creſcite &amp; multiplicamini:</hi> by the lineal inheritance of which, the whole man does propagate the whole man. And were it not a fruſtration of the <hi>Energy</hi> of the Almighties bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, if our opinions concede the Soul <hi>deduceable,</hi> from any <hi>Extrinſec cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For whatſoever belongs to the <hi>eſſential integrity</hi> of human nature,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170136:25"/>doth man propagate by generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but not only the body, but the Soul alſo is <hi>eſsentiall</hi> to human <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity. Ergo,</hi> the ſoul is alſo propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated by generation. <hi>Hence Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcen. Lib. de Orth. Fide,</hi> defines gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to be <hi>ex concurſu maris et fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minae ſimilis ſubſtantiae individui pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creationem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither is the Souls <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>or tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent excellence</hi> to be derived from her Creation: For not <hi>quicquid crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eſt immortale;</hi> but rather every created nature, if we regard its principal, is <hi>per ſe</hi> mortal: and the reaſon why ſome natures are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, others immortal, is not dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible from the <hi>condition</hi> of their <hi>materials,</hi> but from the <hi>omnipotent, ſic placuit, and voluntary decretal</hi> of the Creator; who created whatſoever, whenſoever, and howſoever he pleaſed. And ſuch is the human nature, as the eternal will of God reſolved it, and firmly conſerving the eſſence granted, is according to the <hi>institutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame wil propagated.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Argu. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Our other <hi>firmer Baſis;</hi> on which our affirmation of the Souls <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170136:26"/>relies, is the propagation and hereditary tranſmiſſion of ſin together with the Soul, from our fiſt Grandfather <hi>Adam,</hi> to all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and is erected by an argument, betraying to <hi>impoſsibility or abſurdity,</hi> thus.</p>
               <p>If the Soul be created by infuſion, or infuſed by Creation; God either created the Soul evil and depraved, or infuſed a tincture of evil into it, after it was created: both which, while they allow God to be the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate <hi>original</hi> of the Soul, inferre a dangerous impiety, and conclude him the <hi>Author</hi> of ſin. Or ſecondly, the Soul being by her creation, <hi>perfect, white, and immaculate,</hi> doth contract her <hi>inquination, corruption, and blemiſhes</hi> from the body. But according to the Canon Law of Metaphyſicks, no <hi>material</hi> can <hi>agere</hi> on an <hi>immaterial,</hi> by a <hi>natural act.</hi> True it is, by a general confeſſion, that the cuſtomary inclinations of the mind, do more then frequently confeſſe their ſubjection to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the conſtitution of the body, but this is done <hi>actu morali,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170136:26"/>by <hi>inclination</hi> and <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> not by <hi>impreſſion</hi> of any <hi>real, Phyſical, miaſme,</hi> or <hi>pollution:</hi> by the ſame way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſtars rule us, and God the ſtarres.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. Our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. <hi>V.</hi> 2. expreſly declares, that from the <hi>Heart,</hi> as from a polluted fountain, do ſpring the ſtreams that render man ſullied and impure; and that which commeth out of the mouth defileth man, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>mind,</hi> and radical <hi>Concupiſcence,</hi> are the common ſources, from which all ſin is derivative.</p>
               <p>Or thirdly, we muſt compulſively concede, that ſin is tranſmitted or deſcended from <hi>Adam,</hi> to us, by way of <hi>imitation,</hi> not <hi>propagation</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction:</hi> which error of <hi>Pelagius</hi> is hiſſed out of the Schooles by the Arminians.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Peter du Moulin</hi> conceives to himſelf an eaſie protection from the danger of theſe rocks, by affirming that God created the Soul morally, good and perfect, but (by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of <hi>Adams</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitous fall) deſtitute of ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170136:27"/>light; and therefore becauſe the Soul is, by the natural ſwindge of Eſſential appetite, rapt on to good; but for want of the manuduction of divine light <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is purblind, and inſufficient to ſteer it ſelfe to the true ſupream good, <hi>viz.</hi> God; it violently purſues the creatures, <hi>viz. Bonum jucundum et utile:</hi> and thus by aberration from, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliction of the principal and true good, doth become ſpiritually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved and tainted.</p>
               <p>But this way of evaſion is unſafe, upon a maturer ſounding, and this reſolve (without impeachment of the honour due to ſo much learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) too narrow a <hi>tablet</hi> to pourtraict the nature of Original ſin on; as if it could be nothing but barely the <hi>privation</hi> of <hi>ſupernatural light,</hi> by the dictates whereof, it might <hi>direct</hi> to, and <hi>fix</hi> on the <hi>ſummary good,</hi> where the Soul is purely <hi>paſſive:</hi> When <hi>Gen. Chap.</hi> 8. <hi>Verſe</hi> 22. it is intituled, <hi>Figmentum Cordis, the contrivment or Poeſie</hi> of the heart, evill, and totally corrupted from the Cradle; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, like a Potter, it moulds, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170136:27"/>and actuates luſts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence; as if in our ſoul were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a conformative</hi> power, whereby our hearts can faſhion and proportion evil. Truly the cauſe <hi>procatarctica,</hi> or provocative, is from without; but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and preconceptive,</hi> is in the very Soul.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. That univerſal determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Divines, that the Soul in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturalibus eſt <hi>deprivata,</hi> in naturalibus <hi>depravata:</hi> Whence therefore is this Cymmerian dimnes and obſcurity of the underſtanding; even in the buſineſſe of her own proper objects <hi>(viz) naturals and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligibles,</hi> to which is no way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the aſſiſtance of <hi>divine light?</hi> when our <hi>ingenerated protogenitor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> (before his tranſgreſſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a black cloud over his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and obnubilated its primitive clarity) was exactly read and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in the natures of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, and hence <hi>accommodated appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations</hi> to each diſtinct ſpecies.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. Why in the Sacrament of Baptiſm doth the element of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170136:28"/>
                  <hi>Symbolize waſhing, clenſing,</hi> and <hi>purging,</hi> unleſſe in implicite relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our <hi>uncleanneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera</hi> of our <hi>polluted Nature,</hi> the <hi>reaty,</hi> or <hi>guilt,</hi> though not the <hi>reality,</hi> whereof is abſterged and expunged by Baptiſm? And were it not a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rergie,</hi> we could urge the ſame of Circumciſion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, if we perpend the nature, and ſymptomes of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive crime of <hi>Adam,</hi> we ſhall diſcover a <hi>tract</hi> or <hi>view</hi> of it deeply <hi>impreſſed</hi> in all his ſucceſſion; ſo that thence we may ſympathetically confeſſe it to be <hi>malum haereditarium,</hi> an evil radically and lineally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to all poſterity: <hi>a deſire of knowledg, a palliation, and extenuation of the fact, a tranſlation</hi> of the guilt on others, <hi>et quod nemini obtrudi poteſt; on God himſelfe.</hi> All which are the <hi>Veſtigia</hi> of the firſt ſin, and evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude in the phraſe of the ſacred <hi>Hiſtoriographer, Gen. Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. that <hi>Adam</hi> begot ſons in his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, after his own <hi>image:</hi> which <hi>image,</hi> all Divines conclude, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <hi>Original ſin,</hi> and the <hi>penalty</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170136:28"/>of <hi>eternal</hi> death, which he propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his iſſue, in the room of that <hi>Majeſtick image of Divinity,</hi> received at his firſt inauguration to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
               <p>Our other poſition (in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of which we are likely to end our daies) is,<note place="margin">Theſis <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Animam humanam initio Conceptionis ſtatim adeſſe:</hi> that the human Soul is preſent in the very firſt moment of conception, aſſoon as the <hi>prolifick ſeminary Emiſsions</hi> of both ſexes are mixed, by mutuall <hi>incorporation,</hi> prepared to <hi>Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>conſerved</hi> in the womb, when the <hi>operation conformative</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins; and that there can be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſigned no other <hi>cauſe efficient,</hi> which ſhould enterpriſe the <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> but the <hi>rational Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For whereſoever the proper ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the human Soul are, there muſt her preſence be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged alſo; but in the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception her operations are viſible. <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſhe muſt then, and there be preſent alſo.</p>
               <p>The <hi>operations</hi> of the Soul in the Conception, are (1.) the <hi>conformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170136:29"/>of the <hi>membranous,</hi> ſcarfs that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade and <hi>enſhroud</hi> the Embyro (2.) The <hi>Embryo</hi> it ſelfe. (3.) the <hi>augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of it, for a <hi>Meridian</hi> truth it is, that no ſooner are the parts of the Infant <hi>delineated,</hi> and their <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments</hi> proportion'd, but they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe to <hi>majoration,</hi> or <hi>augmentation;</hi> but in the augmentation, the Soul is communicated to the <hi>acceding</hi> parts; wherefore it is neceſſary that thoſe parts which <hi>accreſce,</hi> or are aditional, ſhould partake <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> in the very firſt <hi>augmentation.</hi> For how it grates the harmonious ears of reaſon, to allow the infant after birth, to be <hi>Majorated</hi> by the influence of another Soul, then that by which it was augmented in the womb.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Conformation</hi> begins with the <hi>Conception,</hi> we are ſolemnly invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to concede, as well from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant and early <hi>activity</hi> of Nature, (in which <hi>idleneſſe</hi> can be imagined with no leſſe abſurdity then <hi>Empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>) as by the <hi>autopticall</hi> obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Abortive Embrio's. Hippocrates Lib. de Natura Pueri, deſcribes</hi> the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170136:29"/>which his Faemal Harper, by obeying his Pagan preſcript, on the ſixth day, after Conception, danced to abortion, in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thus; as if one pil of the outward, ſhel of an Egge raw, in which the humour contained in the inward membrane is tralucent: very like this was that liquour, moreover red and round: but there were viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble white thin Fibres contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the membrane it ſelfe, on the outward part diſcoloured with blood like thoſe that are bloodſhot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in the middle of which was diſcerned ſome ſlender thing, which I conceived to be the navil, and that by it, the Embryo did firſt tranſpire, and from this proceeded
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170136:30"/>the membrane that totally inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Geniture. And <hi>lib. de Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus,</hi> he poſitively delivers, that the conceived, hath on the ſeventh day all parts requiſite to integrity, and that an abortion of this ſepte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary age, put in clear water to a ſubtle inſpector, exhibits all the rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the organical parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faelix Olater in quaeſt. medic. quaeſt.</hi> 1. Preſents the ſeptenary ſlips, which he hath frequently ſervey'd, thus. Firſt, the Plaſtick, or <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative faculty</hi> obſcurely <hi>ambuſcadoed</hi> in the ſeed, <hi>iſſues</hi> forth &amp; <hi>Marſhals</hi> the nobler parts of the ſeed, which flowed from the <hi>three principal members</hi> of the Parents, into <hi>three bullous conglobations, or ſpherical appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions,</hi> which are the rudiments of the <hi>Brain, Heart,</hi> and <hi>Liver;</hi> and <hi>rangeth</hi> the other adherent portions into <hi>Limbs,</hi> which attain perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (<hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>delineation</hi>) the firſt week ſo that the <hi>Embryo</hi> then elapſed, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth an <hi>Orbicular, concreted, infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous maſſe,</hi> diſtinguiſhed with theſe three <hi>globes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The more exquiſite inſpection
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170136:30"/>of <hi>Sennertus</hi> (that great Secretary to Nature) advanced his Scrutiny to to a nearer familiarity with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired abſtruſity of Generation: for in an <hi>Embryo,</hi> not many daies after Conception, effluxed, hee delighted his eyes with the full viſion of theſe three <hi>Orbes,</hi> four <hi>other portions aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the arms and leggs, and two mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute black ſpots,</hi> or <hi>atomicall puncto's</hi> in the <hi>Surpeam Orbe,</hi> which he (and on good reaſon) conceived to bee the <hi>delineated rudiments</hi> of the eies.</p>
               <p>This being thus, it reſults a ſerene and Calme Truth, that the <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> or <hi>Organization</hi> of the <hi>infant</hi> begins in the very <hi>punctilio</hi> or firſt <hi>moment</hi> of <hi>Conception.</hi> And this whiſpered to <hi>Macrobius Lib. in ſomn: Scipion. Cap.</hi> 6. his aſſertion; that ſeed, which does not within ſeven hours after <hi>injection relaps,</hi> is to bee accounted <hi>animated</hi> and <hi>enlivened.</hi> And of our faith was <hi>Lod. Mercatus Lib. de Morb. Mulier. Cap.</hi> 6. for hee concludes thus; when the ſperme of both ſexes is admitted into the wombe, by the vigorous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnating warmth of the ſame
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170136:31"/>cheriſhed, regulated, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſeven hours effuſed, we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the woman hath perfectly conceived. For this reaſon <hi>Hippocr. lib. de Genitura</hi> inſtructs us, to compute the Conception, not from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day; but from the intromiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and retention of the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Neither are we deſtitute of the Soveraign hands of reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to erect this our opinion.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Tertul. Lib: de Anima.</note> For <hi>Tertullian</hi> conlcudes <hi>in ipſo &amp; ex ipſo ſeri hominem; &amp; vium eſſe a primordio ſemen &amp;</hi> Gregory Nyſſen:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Gregor. Nyſſen. Lib. de An. &amp; reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione.</note> 
                  <hi>poſterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem eſſe originem Animarum, ipſaque recentiores eſſe Corporum conſtitutione, nemoſanamente praeditus in animum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duxerit; cum manifeſtum ſit, nihil ex inanimis vim in ſeſe habeat movendi, item<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> creſcendi,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That there can be no other <hi>Effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cauſe</hi> properly aſſigned, which ſhould attempt and finiſh the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formative Work,</hi> but the Rationall Soul is clear from this; that the Adverſaries to this aſſertion break that ſtatute, <hi>Entia non ſunt temerè, &amp; citra neceſſitatem multiplicanda,</hi> and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170136:31"/>incurre the praemunire of thoſe, who on a miſtake of <hi>Ariſt. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Gen. Animal. C.</hi> 3. <hi>Hominem primò vivere anima Vegetante, hinc ſentiente, tertiò Rationalem accipere,</hi> abſurdly dream a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Souls in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man body.</p>
               <p>Thus ſolid <hi>Reaſon, Experience</hi> made up with ſtubble, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied obſervations, and learned <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity,</hi> Conſpire in one firm trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Baſis to become our Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on's ſupportment. On which to proceed to ſuperſtructure; though it might mount our ſpeculation ſome degrees nearer Divinity, then any other pillar in the whole Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre of ſublunary knowledge: yet it would tranſgreſſe the rule of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction,</hi> which forbids the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſociety of <hi>Enlargement.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is time we humbly reſign it, to receive <hi>Ornament</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> from the bounty of ſome more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hand.</p>
               <p>And thus have we glanced on the Soul in a thinn, blew Lanskip, and through the obſcurity of her <hi>Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> To gaze on the naked and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170136:32"/>lively glories of her entire <hi>Nature,</hi> ſuch as it is when ſtrugled from the Eclipſe of Fleſh, mortality is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualified; and we muſt ſuſpend, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till our eſtate of Glory. For <hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe enlarged ſpeculations ſoared in a Sphear, ſuperior to that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our dull Conceptions flagg, could approach her radiant beauty onely by a faint reflexion, thus <hi>Wiſdom cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <hi>She is the breath of the power of God, and a pure influence flowing from the Glory of the Almighty.</hi> ver. 26. <hi>She is the brightneſſe of the everlaſting light; the unſpotted mirror of the power of God, and the image of his goodneſſe.</hi> ver. 27. <hi>And being but one, ſhe can do all things: and remaining in her ſelf, ſhe maketh all things new,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Wherefore let us turn over leafe, to our eaſier Leſſon, the Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170136:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Human Body and its Functions.</head>
               <p>THE Human Body is, by the Eternall Architect, contrived and compoſed of Parts (1.) <hi>Similar</hi> or ſimple, which are ſo ſubdiviſible,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Similaris.</note> that every minute, atomicall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is of the ſame ſubſtance with the whole: (2.) <hi>Diſſimilar,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Diſſimilaris.</note> Organicall, or inſtrumental, which may be reſolved, or undone, into leſſer compound parts ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially different; as the Hand may not bee divided into other hands, but into Bones, Muſcles, Veines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the Similar and Diſſimilar, is required Unity and Integrity: to the Similar, conſidered diſtinctly, is required a juſt harmonious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: to the Organicall is required decent Compoſition and comely Conformation; which according to the Variety of Actions, in each di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct member is various and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
               <p>The Temperament,<note place="margin">Temperamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quid?</note> Craſis or
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170136:33"/>Conſtitution, is one moderrte, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious, actually ſimple quality, reſulting from the intenſe degrees of the four firſt Elementary quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by mutuall Action and Paſſion in Commiſtion, refracted and allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And this is double, (1.) that which belongs to the Body. <hi>quatenùs</hi> ſimply mixed and Compound: (2.) that which pertaines to it, <hi>quatenùs</hi> Animate and living. For in death, this vaniſhes together with the life: but in the Carcaſe (untill its univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall reſolution by putrefaction) the parts, a long time, Conſerve the former.</p>
               <p>Though this temper of living man, which reſults from the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and determinate Conſpiracy of all parts, be Hot and Moiſt; and life ſubſiſt in the ſame materiall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: yet there is framed a great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of parts: of which the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit in Temper is the skin, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that of the Hand.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the Claſſis of Hotter parts is firſt ranked the Heart, 2. the Liver, 3. Spleen, 4. Fleſh of the Muſcles, 5. Kidnies, 6. Lunges, 7. Veines,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170136:33"/>8. Arteries, 9. The ſofter oleaginous Fat or Greaſe, 10. The harder Fat or Tallow</p>
               <p n="2">2. The colder are, 1. the Bones, 2. Cartilages or Griſtles, 3. Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, 4. Tendons, 5. Nerves, 6. Membranes, 7. Spinall Marrow, 8. Brain.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The moiſter are, 1. Fat, 2. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of the Bones, 3. Brain, 4. Spinal Marrow, 5. Teſticles, 6. Duggs, 7. Lunges, 8. Spleen, 9. Kidneies, 10. muſculous Fleſh, 11. Tongue, 12. Heart, 13. Softer Nerves.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The dryer are, 1. Bones, 2. Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, 3. Tendons, 4. Membranes, 5. Arteries, 6. Veines, 7. harder Nerves.</p>
               <p>This Temper, proper to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Animate conſiſts of the Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity,<note place="margin">Calidum inna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> (1) innate, or primitive, (2.) influxive or advenient. This Calidity ingenerate, ſubſiſts in the <hi>Callidum innatum.</hi> For by the <hi>Calidum innatum,</hi> we underſtand not a bare quality divorced from, but reſident in its ſubject.<note place="margin">Humidum radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cale.</note> This increated Heat conſiſts of the implanted ſpirit, and primigenious Moiſture; and is (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170136:34"/>defined) the radicall moyſture exquiſitely perfuſEd, daſhed, or incorporated with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantate Spirit,<note place="margin">Spiritus inſitus.</note> and native warmth. For theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi> Heat, Spirit, and Originary Balſame, are by ſo ſubtile, and firm an Union, marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that they admit no poſſibility of divorce or Extraction. Which myſterious trine-unity, the amazed Philoſopher. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Gen. Animal. cap.</hi> 3. calls <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>This Originary heat, diſſemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diffuſed, principally in the ſpermatick parts, called by <hi>Ariſt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: but chiefly radicate and ſeated in the heart (for the ſame reaſon by <hi>Galen</hi> ſurnamed <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Focum Calidi innati:</hi> Is the grand inſtrument, whereby the Soul doth enterpriſe and perform all her actions corporeal, and is the Taper of life, which, while dren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with a wealthy revenue of primitive oyle, diffuſeth a vigorous and orient luſtre. In the ſecond or conſiſtent age, when there is no
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170136:34"/>contributing unto, but a prodigal waſt of, the unctious, pretious fuel, begins to wane, and yeelds but pale and ſickly flames: in the laſt age, or natural maraſm, for extream poverty, winks out, and an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting midnight ſucceeds.</p>
               <p>The influent conſerves, foſters,<note place="margin">Calor influens.</note> and invigorats the congenerate heat, by mediation of the ſpirits, which are moſt ſubtle, volatile bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, materially the moſt refined, meteorized, exalted part of the blood, aſſociated with the Calidum innatum, become the proxim and principal inſtrument in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all actions, and enable the faculties of the Soul to arrive at the ſecond act.</p>
               <p>That theſe ſpirits are the tie or obligation of the Faculties, and that the Faculties flow from the more into the leſſe noble parts, by the coadjutancy of them, is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine popular, yet diſcordant to truth. For ſince the faculties are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable proprieties of the Soul; &amp; ſhe is diffuſively equally reſident in every part, we ſhall affront our
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170136:35"/>reaſon, not to infer, that ſhe is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where richly provided of her own efficacious faculties, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives them not at ſecond hand, or by the indigent way of mutuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Great is the variety of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning theſe ſpirits,<note place="margin">Spiritus numero tres, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </note> for one ſect ſubſtracts them to a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſſe unity, a ſecond multiplies them to a ſuperfluous plurality: a third (and moſt regular) computes a a trinity, to which opinion, as in neereſt cognation to verity, we adhere. For though the originary material of them all be the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> the purified and moſt ſublimed part of the blood: yet they admit a divers impreſſion, and diſtinct form, according to the diverſity of parts, wherein they receive elabora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſpirituouſneſſe, and are comparated and deſtined to divers and diſtinct uſes: and are only (1.) the Natural, (2.) Vitall, (3.) Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal.</p>
               <p>Concerning the exiſtence of the natural Spirit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Naturalis</note> many ſuſpend their determination; and we, although
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170136:35"/>we admit it into the number of ſpirits, muſt acknowledge no ſmall graduall difference betwixt it and the two other, neither do we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede it charged with the ſame office, that the other bear. Generated it is in the liver, contained in the veines, and is a ſubtle ſpiritual bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, produced from the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or rarefaction of the blood, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a ſubminiſtred material to the Vital ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Which all men concede to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated in the left ventricle of the heart, from the Natural ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Vitalis.</note> flowing into the right Ventricle of it, there attenuated and more ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate; and the aire attracted by inſpiration, and dilatation of the Arteries. This ſpirit is not only in the heart, concurring with the innate heat of the ſame, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal inſtrument of all its actions, but by the arteries diffuſed into the whole body, cheriſhes, excites, and impraegnates the congenerate heat in every part, whence it derives the appellation of Calidum influens. This alſo is the prime materiall of the Animal ſpirit.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170136:36"/>
               <p>The partiality of ſome,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Animalis.</note> to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the prerogative, and enlarge the dominion of the Vital, would anihilate the Annimal ſpirit, but ſince there is aſſigned a peculiar royal organ, the Brain, to its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration and elaboration, and it is inſervient to thoſe noble uſes, which the Vital cannot enterpriſe (for a member, though hountifully perfuſed, and vivified by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, yet deſtitute of the influx of the Animal ſpirits, ſuffers aboliſhment of ſence and motion, as in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy, Palſey, and ſtupor we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but diſcover) we have reaſon to acknowledge not only its exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, but ſoveraignty, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it to be the immediate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of ſenſe and motion, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated of the purer vital ſpirit, tranſlated by the Carotides and neck arteries, firſt into the baſis, then into the ſubſtance of the brain, and of the aire inſpired by the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills.</p>
               <p>To the organical parts is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their peculiar ſingular conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Partss Organice</note> which is a fit compoſure and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170136:36"/>connexion of the homogeneous parts, into one form convenient to the performance of their proper actions. And to this compoſition conſpire (1.) a definit number of the parts component, (2.) a juſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, (3.) a decent conformation which includes (1.) a comely Figure, or exact proportion (2.) the cavities and ſluces, (3.) a ſuperficies ſmooth or rough, according as the nature of the part requires (4.) the ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (5.) the connexion with other parts.</p>
               <p>Thus far our pen has ranged in the blunt declarement of generals; that is, of things common to all parts, and neceſſary to all actions in the body; our Clue of method will henceforward conduct us into ſharper angles, and the preciſe, though brief, enumeration of the particular parts, by which, and in what manner, the particular fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions diſcharge their duties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170136:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Nutrition.</head>
               <p>ANd ſince,<note place="margin">Facultas Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tativa.</note> by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is ordained Guardian paramont of our minority, and obtaines ſituation, as in the loweſt region of our body: ſo alſo at a neerer diſtance to our knowledge, we ſhould invert the method of Life, Anatomy, and Reaſon, not to aſſigne the Van of our ſucceeding lines, to the vegetative faculty</p>
               <p>Under this are comprehended the ſubſervient faculties (1.) Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritive, (2.) Augmentative, (3.) Generative. And firſt concerning Nutrition and Augmentation. Since theſe mutations ariſe from the extraneous acceſſion of Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that at firſt application, is heterogeneous and alien to our ſubſtance, that it may be elabora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſubdued to a qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on analogous, and an aptitude for aſſimilation, it muſt firſt ſuffer the impreſſions of many concoctions.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170136:37"/>
               <p>And this concoction is (1.) pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,<note place="margin">Conoctio.</note> which is made in every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular part. (2.) Publick, which is ordained for the common uſe of the whole body, and is chiefly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the ſtomack and ſpleen.</p>
               <p>The firſt digeſtion therefore is made in the ventricle or ſtomack,<note place="margin">Appetitus.</note> which for this reaſon is endued with a twofold appetite, (1.) Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Naturalis.</note> whereby it is provoked to the acquiſition of aliment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Animalis.</note> ſufficient for it ſelfe. (2. Animal, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites and ſtimulates it to the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and admiſſion of proviſion, for the ſupportment of the whole body, and inſtauration of the threefold ſubſtance, which the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant activity of our native chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry devours.</p>
               <p>For when man,<note place="margin">Manducatio.</note> to lenifie the ſharp vellication, and ſilence the convulſive importunity of hunger, receives in food; the firſt prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or alteration of it is made in the mouth, for there it under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes manducation, fraction, or contrition by the teeth, which for this reaſon (though they concur to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170136:38"/>the formation of ſpeech alſo) are given to man, to the number (in moſt practical conſtitutions) of thirty two, in each jaw ſixteen, ſome whereof are called inciſores, Cutters,<note place="margin">Dentes.</note> others canini, dogs teeth, and the remnant Molares, grinders; the cutters or fore-teeth, are foure in each jaw, the Canine, two, the grinders ten: Moreover the meat is altered by the permiſtion of the ſalivous humidity contained in, and by the heat of the mouth; and being thus bruiſed and maſticated, it is immediately by the auxiliary motion of the tongue, detruded by the then gaping throat, into the ſtomach:<note place="margin">Deglutio.</note> This thus prepared, the ſtomach by the miniſterial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of oblique Fibers, wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes with cloſe embracement and coarctation, and firmly retains, until by its concoctive faculty and proper heat,<note place="margin">Chylificatio.</note> it be transformed into a maſſe, or conſiſtence, not much unlike the cream of a decoction of blanched barly, which is called the Chylus.</p>
               <p>The Chylus thus exquiſirely
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170136:38"/>Crooked, is by the Pylorus Janitor, or inferior orifice of the ſtomach, diſcharged into the inteſtines or guts, and by their immutative acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, attaines one degree more of elaboration and fermentation. The inteſtins are double or rather of two ſorts, (1.) Thin,<note place="margin">Inteflina.</note> which are three, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Duodenum dodek adaktylon,</hi> or gut, of twelve fingers length, (though in the minorated &amp; dwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh race of man in our ſickly age, it be found far ſhort of that meaſure) then <hi>Jejunum,</hi> or empty; thirdly, the <hi>Ileon,</hi> or circumgyrated gut. (2.) Craſs or thick, which are three alſo; Firſt the <hi>Caecum,</hi> or blind; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the <hi>Colon,</hi> or Collick; Thirdly, the <hi>Rectum,</hi> or ſtraight gut.</p>
               <p>But ſince no meat,<note place="margin">Excrementa primae Coction</note> though the pureſt, can be all converted into aliment, but yeelds ſome dregs and excrementitious reſidence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together uſeleſſe to the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the body: Choice nature like a ſubtle Chymiſt, in this firſt, as in both the other concoctions, extracts the benign and wholeſome
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170136:39"/>parts, but rejects the unprofitable and faeculent: <hi>viz.</hi> the thinner and lixivious by urine, the groſſer and terren by ſtool.</p>
               <p>The excluſion of the faeces is done,<note place="margin">Excluſio Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum alvi.</note> partly by the inteſtines, in their ſuperiour parts, contracting and coanguſtating themſelves by the circular and tranſverſe Fibres wherewith both their inward and outward coats are furniſhed; and partly by the mutual aid of the Muſcles of the Abdomen, by which the belly is compreſſed.</p>
               <p>The thinner aquoſity, or tartare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lixivium,<note place="margin">Vina materia.</note> is not preſently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, but incorporated with the Chylus, becomes the vehicle to it, whereby thinned and diluted, it may with the more eaſe, and leſſe danger of obſtruction, permeate, or glide through the narrow veines of the meſentery and liver.</p>
               <p>The firſt concoction thus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved or finiſhed,<note place="margin">Cococtio.</note> the Chylus is, by the vermicular exuction of the lacteous, or milky ſlender veines, which in infinite number are with open orifices inſerted into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170136:39"/>attracted, prediſpoſed to ſanguification, and (per <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) by diſtribution, convey'd to the Liver.</p>
               <p>But that the milky liquor may arrive at the Liver,<note place="margin">Lie nis Vſus.</note> the more pure &amp; defecated, in its journey thither, the Craſs and faeculent part, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the lixiviated ſeroſity, is extracted by, and by the ſplenie branch, derived into the ſpleen, which converts it (that is, ſo much of it as the ſpleens Haematopoietick power can conquer, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory matter ſubmit unto) into blood for the maintenance of it ſelf, and the other vulgar parts in the lower region. And thus the ſpleen doth not only drein and purifie, but is alſo enriched with the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſanguification, and doth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate blood, though courſer and more fixible then that of the Liver: But the remainder which is wholy excrementitious and unconvertible, is ſecluded, partly into the Hoemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoid veines, partly into the trunc of the Port vein, and partly by the ſplenetick arteries.</p>
               <p>The Chylus, by the officiall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170136:40"/>of the ſpleen,<note place="margin">Sanguificatio.</note> thus clarified is delivered up to the Liver, and by the tranſubſtantiating Haematopoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſy thereof, perfectly metamorpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into blood, which from thence by the aſcendent, and deſcendent trunc of the hollow veine, and its capillary diſſeminations, is by univerſal diſtribution communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to all parts of the body.</p>
               <p>But as in every concoction,<note place="margin">Bilis Flava.</note> ſo in this of ſanguification, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound two invincible ſuperfluities, (1.) Choler, or the fiery excrement, which is collected into thee <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> bilious receptacle, or gall, and (after a convenient intervall of time) from thence, through the cholerick chanell, excerned into the duodenum gut, becomes the bodies natural glyſter, and by its acrimony, extimulates the bowels to the excluſion of ordure. (2.) The ſalt whey, or lixiviated ſeroſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which is through the emulgent veines, ſucked in by the Kidneys, in them percolated, and from them diſcharged through the Vreters, into the Urinary receptacle, or
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170136:40"/>bladder, and then called Vrine.<note place="margin">Serum.</note> For the Urine is nothing elſe, but the Aquoſity or ſerous Humidity of the Chyle,<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rina.</note> impregnated or ſatisfied with the ſuperabundant and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtible ſalt of our diet. And this is familiar to vulgar diſquiſition, not onely from the affections and ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes occaſioned by it; but from the large quantity of ſalt drawn of Urine, when the aqueous humidity is Evaporated.</p>
               <p>The blood,<note place="margin">Sanguis.</note> which for the generall ſuſtenance thereof,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Temperatus.</note> is diſtributed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whole body;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Bilioſus.</note> although con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3,</hi> Melancholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> and managed by one ſingle form; yet diſparted is Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogeneous,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Pituitoſus.</note> and the more benigne and temperate diviſion of it is blood properly and diſtinctly ſo called; the igneous or hot and dry is called Choler; the Aqueous or cold and moiſt is called phlegme; the Terrene or cold and dry is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Melancholy. And of all theſe, there is no part Excrementitious or unalimentary; but (while under the wholſome Government and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lawes of Eucraſie) is
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170136:41"/>wholy digeſtible and nutritive.</p>
               <p>This Blood or Soveraign Nectar, being Circulated,<note place="margin">Circulatis ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis. de qua vid. Epiſt. Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laei ad Thom. Bartholin. &amp; Lib. doctiſſimi noſtr: Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici Guliel. Harveij Angli.</note> a voyage or two, through the numerous, ſlender me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders, and Capillary divarications of the Veines and Arteries, is wafted to each individuall part: according to the Craſis of each diſtinct part, admits a peculiar diſtinct impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and is at length tranſubſtantiated and aſſimilated.</p>
               <p>But ſince in this Elaboration,<note place="margin">Humores Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundarij.</note> the blood undergoes ſucceſſive tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations; Philoſophy conced's the Generation of four ſecundary Humors ſucceeding each other in exiſtence: and that the blood by theſe four mutations doth gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally aſcend to Aſſimilation.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Innominatus.</note> The firſt of theſe Humors is called (aſſuredly the firſt Imponent had no very large nomenclature, ſince he was driven to aſſign it this name) <hi>Anonymos,</hi> Nameleſſe, the ſecond is called <hi>Ros,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Ros.</note> the Dew,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Gluten.</note> the third <hi>Gluten,</hi> or the viſcid &amp; glutinous, the fourth <hi>Cambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Cambium.</note> becauſe it exchanges its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for that of the part to which it is applyed.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170136:41"/>
               <p>And in this laſt, and moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Concoction alſo, there remaines a pleonaſmus, or redundancy of excrements, the one whereof are thoſe ſtrigments and ſordid adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to the skin:<note place="margin">Strigmenta.</note> the other is that watery ſerous matter, which is partly diſcuſſed, <hi>per,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by inviſible tranſpiration, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excluded by ſweat.<note place="margin">Sudor.</note> And for the Convenient Evacuation of theſe Excrements the skin was conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted porous and tranſpirable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of Generation.</head>
               <p>AND God ſaw every thing that he had made,<note place="margin">Generatio.</note> and behold it was very good. This is the reaſon why the Creature ſo abhors diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and endeavours to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate its Verity, that is, conformity to the primitive idea in the ſupreme intellect. For ſo much bettr is it to be, though in the miſerable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſomething, then in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170136:42"/>horrid obſcurity of nothing; that (if ſome gueſſe aright) the Devill, though he might evade his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, would not conſent to his own annihilation.</p>
               <p>But ſince this deſire of eternity can, in ſublunary Animals, be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied onely in part (for individualls muſt periſh upon their own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the ſame flames which kindled them to life muſt become their funerall Taper, and light them back to elements) Nature hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived a way to immortality, by the ſucceſſion of the ſpecies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated by Generation. And by this way man (whoſe ingredients con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his mortality, not onley ſince, but before his Fall) relieves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from totall regreſſion into the oblivion of his firſt Chaos, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſuperior to the tyranny of Corruption, by the immortality his iſſue.</p>
               <p>Now this Generation or act of the Vegetative Faculty is performed by the ſeminality of Male and Female,<note place="margin">Semen principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Generation is quid?</note> inheriting fertility from the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170136:42"/>benediction of the Creator, <hi>in Creſcite &amp; multiplicamini.</hi> And this Generative materiall as made of the pureſt part of the blood and fineſt ſpirits both Vitall and Animall, flowing by the veines,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Sennertus Lib. Inſt. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Qui ſemen fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mininum proli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficum eſse, vim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que agendi in ſe continere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimant, ij mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi prohabilio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem defendere ſententiam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur. Et non ſolùm eo nituntur quod ſemen faemininum à ſimilibus organis generetur, atque in venere cum eadem oblectatione excerna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Nos ſtatuimus utrumque ſexum ſuum ad Generationem conferre <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; neutrius ſexus ſemen ſeorſim ſumptum, ſed utriuſque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctum, &amp; in utero Faeminae ritè unitum, eſſe ſemen prolificum &amp; fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuncum. &amp;c. <hi>Plato.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> Atteries and Nerves, into the Teſticles; whereby their Spermatopoietick power it is converted into a white, ſpumous, ſpirituous ſubſtance, containing the perfect Idea of each individuall part.</p>
               <p>This prolific Contribution <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> will not allow the Faemale ſex; but conceives their parts onely recipient for the maſculine injecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but if wee conſult our reaſon and our ſence wee cannot but atteſt the contrary. For Femalls have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments officiall both to ſpermifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Emiſſion; are invited to,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170136:43"/>and act Congreſſion with the ſame libidinous orgaſmus, and pleaſant fury, that the Males do: and their Seminary Emiſſions ahve been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to the ocular ſcrutiny of many. Neither do Male and Female differ in <hi>ſpecie,</hi> but <hi>ſexu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet the ſingleſeed of either ſex is not ſufficient to procreation; but ſuch is the inſtitution of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, that from the united Seminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Male and Female, as from two partiall Cauſes mutually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing their Efficiencies, one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and third totall Cauſes ſhould reſult: from which one motion or mutation, though diſtinctly regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhould advance to the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the infant. For the efficiency of the maſculine injection carries the greater ſtroak in Conformation, and is more virtuall then the Femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine.</p>
               <p>The prolifick Ejaculations of both ſexes received into the womb,<note place="margin">Conceptio.</note> are, by the proper innate produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive faculty thereof conſerved, and cheriſhed; and the plaſtick Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mator, which lay concealed in the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170136:43"/>ſeed is called forth, excited, and impregnated, and begins the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neation or organization of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant.<note place="margin">Ordo Formatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> The parts firſt formed are the two membranes, in which the more divine and ſpiritual parts of the ſeed are inwrapped, that enſhroud the Infant;<note place="margin">Membrana Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> one whereof is called the Amnios, or Lawn ſhirt, that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately inveſts the Infant: the other Chorion, or the girdle, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolls it, and is the ſupportment of the Umbelick veſſels, and the cauſe of its adhaeſion to the Cotyledones, or cakes of the womb; which two involutions conjoyned, make the ſecundine or after-birth.</p>
               <p>The feminine prolification thus expanſed into filmy integuments,<note place="margin">Partes ſpermati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae, delineantur.</note> and the new kindled Diety en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheared; the ſpermatick parts ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſeniority of conformation, and are ſpun out into a numberleſſe number of fine ſlender filaments, which are the <hi>ſtamina,</hi> or ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of the ſolid parts, and (by a Texture farre too fine and cunning for the fingers of <hi>Arachne</hi>) woven into three bullous orbs or conglobations.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170136:44"/>
               <p>Theird delineation thus diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">Sanguis mater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> the parts, by the nutritive ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the other fertile princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the maternal blood, advance to increment and majoration. And for this purpoſe, the wiſe contriver of both worlds hath ordained, from the fourteen to the forty-fifth year of life, in eucratical bodies, a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Plethora, and providence exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancy of blood,<note place="margin">Menſtruorum cauſa finalis.</note> in teeming and ingravidated women, to become the Infants ſuſtentation: or in vacancy of praegnation, leſt it overcharge and prove offenſive, to be by perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dick monthly conflux tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the womb, and thence excluded.</p>
               <p>The infant having from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther received the rudiments of the ſanguineous parts,<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſa umbiliea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Vena umbili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calis.</note> the conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor frames a vein,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Arteriae duae.</note> two arteries, and the urachus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Vrachus.</note> convening about the navill, and wreaths them into one contorted umbilicality, or quadri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partit Navill ſtring: the vein being a ſurcle of the Port vein, and inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the fiſſure of the Liver, is the Nurſe provided to ſuckle
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170136:44"/>the Infant. The arteries are two twinn branches of the Iliacall deſcendent Arteries, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits by which the beſt portion of the arteriall blood and ſpirits is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to the Heart of the new pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction: The Uracus is a derivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Bladder to the Navill. After parturition, the uſe of all theſe ceaſing, they are by coalition and exiccation degenerated into Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>The age (or more truly the non-age) of the Infant in the womb is diſtinguiſhed into the time (1.) of Formation,<note place="margin">Tempus forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</note> which extends from the Conception to the Calcitration, or quickening; and (2.) of Exorna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or perfection, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted from the motion, to partu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition. Others otherwiſe divide it into the time (1.) of formation,<note place="margin">Tempus calcis trationis.</note> which in the account of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> laſts to the thirtieth day in Maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, and to the fortieth in Femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine Conceptions. (2.) Of moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the vulgarity of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians concede to be in the third month in males, in the fourth in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170136:45"/>females. (3.) of parturition, which is ſo various, that whoſoever can definitively calculate <hi>nobis erit Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Apollo.</hi> The wiſe ignorance of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> confirms the incertitude thus. <hi>Lib. de Alimento ad conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem. Soles triginita quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>: ad moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem ſeptuaginta, ad perfectionem du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi decem. Alti tradunt ad formam</hi> 45, <hi>ad motionem.</hi> 76. <hi>ad exitum</hi> 20. <hi>requiri. Alii adſpeciem</hi> 50. <hi>ad primum ſaltum</hi> 100. <hi>ad perfectionem</hi> 30. <hi>Ad diſtinctionem</hi> 40. <hi>ad tranſitionem</hi> 80. <hi>ad elapſum</hi> 240. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But our expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience eſtabliſheth, above the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of eviction, that no concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which hath an immature exit before the expiration of 6 months partaks vitality.<note place="margin">Hippocr. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> puer ſeptimo menſe natus, certa ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione prodiit &amp; vitalis eſt, cum is rationem &amp; numerum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actè ad hebdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madas reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem liabet. Octavo autem menſe natus numquam vixit. Novem autem menſium &amp; dierum faetus editur &amp; vitalis eſt; numerumque ad hebdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madas exactè reſpondentem habet. Quatuor nempe decades hebdomada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, dies ſunt ducenti &amp; octoginta.</note> That the aborted iſſue of the ſeventh month uſually lives, and may (if virile and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous) be cheriſhed to maturity: that Octomeſtral births are ever fatal, if the Doctrine of <hi>Hippocrates</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170136:45"/>hold good: but that moſt legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, happy,<note place="margin">Tempus partus.</note> and frequent time of Parturition, is the ninth month, and that the enixation, or delivery, uſuall fals out between the fifteenth day of the ninth month, and the fifteenth of the tenth of the geſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>But although in the obſervations of Phyſicians, there ſtand recorded divers undecimeſtrall, duodeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtral, and elder editions: yet ſuch overſhoot mediocrity; and are to be filed in the legend of rarities, and ſportive miracles of nature.</p>
               <p>Though the months, by which we compute the Geſtation, arer ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary; yet from theſe, the lunary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions of twenty nine daies, and twelve howers, are not in the main much diſcrepant: neither is this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious artifice confined to any certain minute, punctilios of time: For as the magnality of human re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemination is withdrawn from our comprehenſion; ſo is the indefinity of its time the diſcouragment of our determination.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170136:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Vital faculty.<note place="margin">Facultatum ordo et dignitas.</note>
               </head>
               <p>THe human Soul,<note place="margin">De facultatum concentu, et principatus or dine videatur Fernelius, lib. <hi>5.</hi> de Animae Facultatibus. Cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> though ſtill an abſolute Monarch, divides her Empire into a triarchy, nd go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns by the diſpenſation of a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umvirate. The three Viceroves, though they are abſolutely diſtinct by their commiſſions, and keep their courts in ſeverall Regions, are by ſo indiſsoluble a league and ſympathetick allyance united, that the proſperity of one enlarges the principalities of the other, and the detriment of each, threatens the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of all. The natural or vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Faculty, claimes ſuperiority in order of procreation, as being go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of our minority, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the firſt tertio of our life: the vital merits preheminence in order of neceſſity, as tranſmitting a ſoveraign, and conſervatory influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, without which, the other muſt, in the fleeteſt article of time be depoſed for ever. The Animal
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170136:46"/>challenges ſupremacy in order of excellency, as regulating the diviner actions, ſence and motion, to which, as to their perfection, the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are deſtined. Thus every one of theſe rulers is ſupream, and yet they are all equal.</p>
               <p>The vital faculty,<note place="margin">Facultas Vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</note> by proper actions, and peculiar Organs, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely diſtinct from the natural &amp; animal, is ſeated in its own royal Throne; the heart. The 3 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Thumetick powers reſident in the Heart, all comprehended under the name vital, are firſt the faculty Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerative of the arterial blood and ſpirits, (2.) of the vital conſervato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heat. (3.) the Pulſifick or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive official to the former.</p>
               <p>From the iraſcible faculty,<note place="margin">Fac. Iraſcibilis.</note> ſtream all the Pathemata, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or paſſions of the mind, Anger,<note place="margin">Animi Pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata.</note> Manſuetude, Audacity, Fear, Hope, Deſpair, Dejection, or Proſtration of the ſpirit, Joy, Sorrow, and others of the ſame Claſſis, that are either compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of, or dependent on the former: Of theſe paſſions, ſome are performed <hi>materialiter, ſeu per modum
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170136:47"/>cauſae efficientis,</hi> by expanſion, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centrick motion of the vital Heat, Blood, and Spirits; of this order are Anger, Joy, &amp;c. others by concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of the ſame, as Fear, Sorrow, &amp;c. but formaliter, all are nothing, but the motions of the Appetite, either in proſecution of the delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and friendly, or flight and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, from the odious and offenſive object, of which the former cauſeth an expanſion, or circumferentiall ſalley, the latter a retraction or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centrick retreat of the vital blood and ſpirits: But theſe appetitions, or iraſcible and concupiſcible mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cannot be executed, but the agitation of the Heart, Arteries, and fervent ſpirituous blood. From this we receive ſatisfaction, why the <hi>Facultas</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of neceſſity hath its reſidence aſſigned in a part of the hotteſt temperature, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the power of perpetual agitation.</p>
               <p>The ſituation of the heart is (though vulgarly deluded by the ſenſation of its pulſe,<note place="margin">Cordis Situs.</note> and the ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter declination of its mucro, or
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170136:47"/>cone, oppinion it to be placed in the left ſide) in the center of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, if in our meaſure we except the thighes and legs; and its Baſis or Center, fixed in the middle of the Thorax, or middle region of the body, that from it as from a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fountain, the vital Heat and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits may be promptly diffuſed into the whole body.</p>
               <p>The ventricles,<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entriculi:</note> cavities or cloſets of the heart, are two, the right and left, the right does by Diaſtole or dilatation, ſuck in blood from the gapeing oſtiary, or floud-gate of the aſcendent hollow vein, by its intenſer fire, cohobate, refine, and rarify it; the more ſubtile and mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orized part whereof, is, through the Foramina, or capillary perfora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſeptum, interſtitiary skreen (which notwithſtanding <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbus, Spigelius, Hoffmannus,</hi> and our <hi>Hippocrates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Septum inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitium.</note> Doctor <hi>Harvie</hi> will by no means admit of) or partition wall betwixt both ventricles, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colated into the left ventricle; the other parcel paſſeth by the <hi>Vena Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terioſa</hi> into the lungs; and one ſmall
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170136:48"/>portion of it converts into the Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lungs, the remainder is tranſported by the <hi>Arteria Venoſa,</hi> into the left Chamber of the heart.</p>
               <p>Theſe buſineſſes (which we are ſorry to confeſſe more the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our wonder,<note place="margin">Cardis motus.</note> then our knowledge) are tranſacted by a certain admirable and unceſſant motion of the Heart; whereby, in the diaſtole,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Diaſtole.</note> the extremities of it are contracted, and the mucro or point ravelled up towards the Baſis, ſo that the Heart in longitude ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviated, and in latitude expanſed: but in the Syſtole or Compreſſion, it is by coanguſtation of the ſides enlarged in longitude,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Syſtole.</note> and diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in latitude.</p>
               <p>But ſince to the regeneration of vitall ſpirits and Arteriall blood are required two neceſſary ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, Venal blood, and the Aer: and theſe two materiall principles cannot, by one and the ſame moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, bee attracted: beſides theſe two Ventricles recipient and elaborato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, there are ſuperadded two nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170136:48"/>Cavities, (Chriſtned by Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts <hi>Auriculae proceſſes</hi> or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions) on each ſide one, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſurperior part of the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricles: The uſes whereof are (1.) to inſpire Aer for the refocillation or recreation of the vitall ſpirits, and to bee the Hearts promptuaries or ſtorehouſes to receive the blood and Aer that they may not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with too ſuddain an impetuoſity ruſh into the heart and cauſe ſuffocation: (2.) to fortifie and guard the <hi>Vena Arterioſa, &amp; Arteria Venoſa,</hi> to which they are adjoyned: (3.) according to the doctrine of <hi>Hippocrates, Lib. de. Corde,</hi> to ſerve the heart in ſtead of a Fan or Refrigeratory; for they are therefore diſtended becauſe imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; whereas the Heart, by a motion quite contrary to this, is therefore impleted becauſe diſtended.</p>
               <p>That the Heart in its Contracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Expanſion might be guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from impediments,<note place="margin">Pericardium.</note> Nature hath conſtituted it a capacious, membra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, domicilium or Tent, called the Pericardium or Purſe of the heart; the uſe whereof is (1.) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170136:49"/>the heart in its motion from the shocks of the circumjacent parts (2.) to contain the ſerous Humor, wherein as in <hi>Balneo,</hi> the heart is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frigerated, moyſtned, and its motion facilitated.</p>
               <p>Moreover, ſince nothing can have ingreſſe to,<note place="margin">Vaſa.</note> and regreſſe from the heart, but through Conduits and Sluces: there are for this purpoſe ordained four conſpicuous veſſells in the Baſis of it, two in the right, and two in the left ventricle of the heart: in the right are the <hi>vena Cava &amp; vena arterioſa:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Vena Cava.</note> in the left, <hi>Arteria magna &amp; Arteria Venoſa.</hi> (1.) The hollow veine with an ample and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent orifice looks into the right ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus of the heart, and into it drops blood for the generation of Arterial blood, the vitall ſpirits, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the Lungs. Others, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, opinion that the blood rediſtilled and elaborated in this preparatorie, is immediately diſtributed through the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Vena arteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis.</note> (2.) the <hi>vena Arterialis</hi> is the derivatory of blood from the right ventricle of the heart, to the Longs,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170136:49"/>for their nutrition, and the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall materiall of the vitall ſpirit and blood:<note place="margin">Arteria venalis.</note> (3.) The <hi>Arteria Venoſa</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts the Aer extrinſecally adveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and prepared in the Lungs, and the blood by the <hi>Vena Arterioſa</hi> effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the right, into the left ventricle; and expells the fuliginous Exhalations, and at the ſameinſtant conveies a parcel of the vital ſpirits into the Lungs:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Aorta.</note> (4.) The Aorta or grand Arterie diſpenſeth the vitall ſpirits, and Arteriall blood, after their Exaltation in the left ventri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, into the whole body. Theſe four Sanguiducts, <hi>Hippocr: Lib. de Corde</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. the Fountaines of Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and fructifying rivulets where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the purple Iland is irriga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>But ſince each of theſe four Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable veſſels is ordained to a double uſe: <hi>Ex. Gr.</hi> the <hi>Arteria Veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> doth not onely ſuck in Aër from the Lungs, and inſpire it into the left Ventricle of the Heart; but alſo returns up the vitall ſpirit;<note place="margin">Valvulae.</note> and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trerial blood to the Lunges, and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170136:50"/>out the ſmoaky Exhalation: that the ſubſtances admitted into the Heart, may not rebound back by the ſame way they entered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have attained full tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and intended perfection; or what is effuſed from the Heart may not remeate into it again, the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient Contriver hath annexed ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Values or Flood-gates to the orifices of theſe veſſels, two to the <hi>Arteria Venoſa,</hi> and three apiece to the other three.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>Vena Cava</hi> are ſigned three, called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, tricuſpides, three-pointed Values, that look inwards, that the blood may have intraction into the right Ventricle, but no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion into the hollow veine: (2.) Contrarily, thoſe of the <hi>Vena Arteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſa,</hi> named, from their figure, Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modies, Semi-Cynthian Values, ſhut inwardly, but open outwardly, that the blood may have Eructation, but be denied readmiſſion: (3.) the two Janitors allowed to the <hi>Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Venoſa,</hi> being conjoined repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent an Epiſcopall Mitre, open out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and ſhut inwardly, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170136:50"/>the reflux of the emitted vitall ſpirit; and fuliginous expiration: (4.) Thoſe affixed to the Grand Arterie, are three ſemicircular or halfmooned, look outwardly, and occlude inwardly, that the Arteriall blood and vitall ſpirit powred out for the vivifying ſupportment of the whole, may not remeat into the left Ventricle.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ductus,</hi> Pipes, or Conduits,<note place="margin">Arteria.</note> through which the heart tranſmits vitall heat ſpirits and blood to the whole body, are branches of the Aorta which are alſo dilated and contracted,<note place="margin">Pulſus quid?</note> and by this motion draw in the Ambient Aer through the ſpiramina or ſlender evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the skin; and diſtribute the vitall ſpirits, and arteriall blood; which motion of the heart and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries is called the Pulſe.</p>
               <p>Which conſiſts of two Contrary motions, a Diaſtole or dilatation,<note place="margin">Arteriarum. <hi>1.</hi> Diaſtole.</note> &amp; a Syſtole or Coanguiſtation, after a momentary reſpite or articulate intervall of time, mutually ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each other. (1.) in the Diaſtole
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170136:51"/>the heart is impleted with Aer and Blood, drawn in from the Lunges by the <hi>Arteria Venoſa:</hi> and the Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries through their ſubcutaneous ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices attract a convenient quantity of the environing Aer. (2.) in the Syſtole the heart,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Syſtole.</note> by the great Arterie, delivers out vitall heate, and Arteriall blood, invigorated with vitall ſpirits, for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of all, and by the <hi>Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Venoſa</hi> diſcharges the ſmoky effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and the Arteries by their ſmall oſtiaries ſqueeze out their vaporous ſuperfluities; which action is termed <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, inſenſible Tranſpiration.</p>
               <p>Again,<note place="margin">Pulmones.</note> in the regard the inſpired Aer muſt part with its intenſe frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, be refracted and ſuffer ſome graduall mutation, before it pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate to the heart; the prudent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formator hath inſtituted Reſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, provided <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Reſpirators, Lungs, as the praeipuous Organs thereof. For although the Thorax and other neighbouring parts may be allowed cauſes <hi>ſine qua non,</hi> and contribut their inſerviency to reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170136:51"/>
                  <hi>modo ſecundario:</hi> yet primarily, as from its Cauſator this motion flowes from the Lungs; to which, as well as to the heart and brain, by the inviolable Charter of Nature, is granted a peculiar innate power to dilate and contract themſelves:<note n="*" place="margin">Et ſi meritò concedamus hanc, de Pulmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; thoracis motu, litem noſtro arbitrio diſcerni non poſſe: tamen motum Pulmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ab inſita iis facultate, non thoracis motum ſequi, proſiciſci, &amp; veritati maximè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneum vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; peritiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vationibus ac rationibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatur.</note> which in living Anatomies, and vulnerary perforations of the Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax, may with eaſie animadverſion be confirmed. For neither is Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration a motion arbritrary or depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent on the injunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our wil; nor are the Lungs dilated <hi>ob fugamvacui,</hi> (which would accuſe Nature of the want of forecaſt, and ſhifting into one abſurdity, to avoid another) when the Thorax is diſtended: but they are moved by their owne inherent virtue reſpiratory, and the Lunges and Thorax are therefore in one, and the ſame inſtant moved, becauſe they conſpire to one and the ſame end: But that this might be with the greater convenience performed; and the Lungs have a room accommodate to their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the Animall Faculty, at the ſame inſtant moves the Thorax.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170136:52"/>Theſe two motions keep time to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and obſerve ſo even a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in Expanſion &amp; Coarction, that ſome have thence hinted the error, that they are regulated by one and the ſame faculty: Neither are the lungs diſtended, becauſe repleted, as a bladder by the infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Aer, but, ſince there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flatorie inſtrument, that ſhould from without puffe Aer into them, are therefore repleted, becauſe dilated, as in a bellous, the cauſe of its repletion is dilation.</p>
               <p>This <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Reſpiration, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of two contrary ſucceſſive motions: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Inſpiration, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Expiration,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Inſpiratio.</note> and a ſhort quies inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening. (1.) In inſpiration, the Lungs and Thorax being dilated, the Aer, by the mouth and noſtrils is drawne in for the fanning and refrigeration of the heart, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the vital ſpirits.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Expiratio.</note> (2.) In Expiration, the Lungs and Thorax being compreſſed, the Fuliginous Excrements (which in winter, when the intenſe frigidity of the furroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding aire condenſes them, are viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble)
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170136:52"/>are by the mouth and noſtrils excluded. And for this reaſon,<note place="margin">Excrementa Fuliginoſa.</note> that both a plentiful proportion of Aer may be ſucked by, and contained in them: the Lungs in magnitude proportionably, exceed any other of the Viſcera, and have obtained a porous, ſpongy ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>The Fiſtula or Cane that conveys the inſpired Aer from the mouth and noſtrils into the lungs,<note place="margin">Aſpera Arteria.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Ejus.</note> is the <hi>Aſpera Arteria,</hi> or <hi>Trachea,</hi> with our Nation, the Weazon, or Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe, whoſe ſuperiour part, from the Larynx to the Bronchi, is one ſingle trunc;<note place="margin">Bronchi.</note> but the inferior is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicated into innumerable ſmaller branches or diſſeminations (by <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Syringae</hi>) and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed into all quarters of the lungs for their total implection with Aer, which the veſſells extended from the heart, receive and defer into the ventricles of it.</p>
               <p>And ſince we cannot, the ſhorteſt account of time, ſurvive the defect of Aer, both to ventilate and allay the fervour of our cordial fire, which would elſe intend to confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170136:53"/>and terrify our heart to Cynders,<note place="margin">Conformationis ratio.</note> and to recruit our vitall ſpirits, ſo prodigally exhauſted: This <hi>Aſpera Arteria</hi> is contrived of many round, annular (or rather ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moidall) Cartilages, connexed by intermediate ligaments, that by this ſtructure, it might be alwaies kept open, and we ſecured from ſtrangulation, which immediately ſucceeds its conciſion.</p>
               <p>But that our deglutition might not prove our deſtruction, and no part of our meat, and no more of our drink, then may only betermed a guttulous irrigation, might drop down into the Trachea, or rough arterie, to the hazard of ſuffocation; providence hath in the upper part of it, framed the Epiglottis, which is a ſoft Cartilagineous flap,<note place="margin">Epiglottis. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Hippocrat. de Morb. Lib, <hi>4</hi> ctrca finem.</note> in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure repreſenting a tongue, or (if we applaud the fancy of <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>) an Ivy leafe, and when we ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low down our meat, ſhuts the chink of the <hi>Aſpera Arteria:</hi> For every morſel that deſcends this forbidden
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170136:53"/>way, hath a dangerous haughtguſt of <hi>Anacreons</hi> grape, and denounceth the ſame harſh fate. Had we ſaid croſſe fate, the Epithite had been more genuine, and would have cleerly hinted the inverſion and prepoſterous rarity; for how unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall and perverted an accident was it, for the invincible ſtupiditie of a Poet to flow from his inſpiration, &amp; a volatile Muſe, to be condenſed into eternal dulneſſe by the ſpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fruit of the Vine; the ſame inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, whoſe active flames had ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten warm'd and exalted her to the ſublimity of rapture.</p>
               <p>Moreover, ſince the Thorax,<note place="margin">Therax.</note> or Cheſt, is, partly the Munimentum or Fortreſſe erected for defence and ſafeguard of the vital parts, and partly an inſtrument to reſpiration; it muſt not have been built totally <hi>Carneous;</hi> for fleſh were too ſoft a materiall to reſiſt the aſſaults of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal injuries; nor totally oſſeous, for bones would admit no ſuch flexure as is required to reſpiration; wherefore it is compoſed of twelve pair of Ribs, or arcular
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170136:54"/>bones, to which, that they might be bent and relaxed, in dilatation and conſtriction, there are adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſixty five Muſcles, whereof thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two diſtend, and as many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the Thorax.</p>
               <p>But becauſe no ribs could,<note place="margin">Diaphragma.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perverting the rules of Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, be planted in the lower part of the Thorax; that in this Region, there might not want an Organ fit, both for diſtention and Contracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo to divide the Vitall from the Naturall parts; there is a partition wall, or muſculous and carneous interſtitiary, therefore called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, drawn tranſverſly betwixt this and the lower region, which in Expiration is elevated, and in inſpiration is depreſſed. And becauſe, the Gullet, Grand Arterie, and Hollow Veine, which in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall transforations paſſe through the midriff, cloſe to the Spine, may not, by the perpetuall motion thereof ſuffer conſtriction and agitation: the Centre of it is membranous &amp; ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, but the periphery or Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference Carneous, that ſo this part
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170136:54"/>may be leſſe ſubject to Contraction, when the other perpetually aſcends and deſcends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the Senſitive Faculty.</head>
               <p>COnducted by the Conſtant ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuduction of Nature, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending by the ſame progreſſionall degrees, by which ſhe advances to the Glory and Crown of her Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, Perfection; we are mounted to the ſupreme Orb of our Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme: wherein, as their proper Sphear, the Rationall, and ſenſitive Faculties exerciſe their Semi-divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: and from whence, by their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt immaterial Agents, the Animal Spirits, they tranſmit their more then Elementary activity. And herein, ſince the firſt part of our Lecture looked, though by a pale and faint reflexion of its actions, and through the Chäos of obſcure bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, on the Rationall Faculty: we conceive it our duty to addreſſe our
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170136:55"/>future ſpeculations onely to the Senſitive; and obſerve how that governs and actuates the members of the body to the deſignes of Senſe and Motion.</p>
               <p>The two Fountains from which, as from their primitive Originals, all the operations of the ſenſitive faculty ſtream, are (1.) the power apprehenſive, (2.) Appetitive or Motive.</p>
               <p>The Apprehenſive is that power,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Vis Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſiva</note> whereby we diſcern and diſtinguiſh of Objects preſent and abſent. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this are comprehended all the Senſes, (1.) Externall, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) the Sight (2.) Hearing, (3.) Taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (4.) Smelling, (5.) Feeling: (2.) Internal, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) Common Senſe (2.) Imagination or Phantaſy, (3.) Memory.</p>
               <p>The Externall Senſes reſiding in the Circumference of the body diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and cenſure Externall objects endued with ſenſibility,<note place="margin">Externi Senſus</note> by their own act, without information from any other Faculty preceding.</p>
               <p>And ſince Senſion is no ſimple action either of the Soul, or of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170136:55"/>body, ſingly and disjunctively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; but reſulting from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive efficiencies and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of both: to the juſt perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it are required (1.) a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Soul (2.) an Organ or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (3.) an Object, (4.) a Medium.</p>
               <p>The firſt and chief requiſite is <hi>Anima,</hi> the Faculty ſenſient,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Anima ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiva.</note> or Effectrix: for this is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>per quam Corpus Animatum ſenſibile extra ſe poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum percipit, &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>actu tale reddit;</hi> the power by which the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate body perceives the ſenſible, Externall Object, and preferrs it from the imperfection of ſenſibility in capacity, to the perfection of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility in act. For no ſooner doth this Efficient or Cauſality take leave of her Concomitant the body: but the body compulſively retires back into the inſenſibility of its cold ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls, and can be reactuated by the information of no Power, ſecond to that, whoſe look can ſpeak the Rocks into Animation.</p>
               <p>The ſecondary Cauſator neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is the Organ or Senſorium;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Organum.</note> for although in regard of Eſſence, the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170136:56"/>Soul be equally omnipreſent in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry atomicall particle of the body: yet is it no where the Author of ſenſe, but where it meets with the proviſion of an Organ. Again, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the eſſence of the ſoul be the ſame in the Foot, that is in the eye or ear: yet becauſe in the Foot it is deſtitute of an inſtrument, it neither ſees nor hears. The inſtruments of ſenſe that we may interpret the thoughts of <hi>Jul. Caeſar Scalig. Excercit.</hi> 297. Sect 3.) are (1.) the Spirits whoſe nature holds a large correſpondency and near affinity to the Facullty it it ſelf: (2.) the members, which are conſtituted in ſome ſimilitude and Cognation to the objects: For the Spirits are ſubtle, inviſible, and ſo exalted ſubſtances, that we may (by the favour of compariſon) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them immateriall. Yet on theſe as on their proper recipient the ideas of ſenſible objects are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; and the inſtrumental mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are but the Conductors and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicles of them towards the Objects. The members, although they are made up of many ſeverall parts ſo
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170136:56"/>neceſſary, that the defect or vitioſity of the meaneſt, induceth aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or depravation on all; yet is their one part above the reſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the praerogative of being the precipuous and approximate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Senſion, and there is in the particular Organ of every ſenſe, one determinate ſimilar part, in which the form of the determinate object is expreſſed:<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſt. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Part. An. cap. <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> and therefore is the Senſorium, if no way digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the integrity of conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, confined within the circle of Analogy, and praerequiſite propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to its proper object, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the peculiar nature of the object, it may ſuffer a peculiar and identical alteration, and entertain the impreſſion of the peculiar Idea, which, by intentional effluviums, or aporrhoias ſtreams from the object.</p>
               <p>The third conſpirator is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Objectum.</note> the ſenſible object, or more ſtrictly, ſenſible diffuſive qualities; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in a randome acception, it be no impropriety to call the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſingular and corporeal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, yet they ſtrike not the ſenſe,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170136:57"/>
                  <hi>quatenus ſubſtances,</hi> but as they are endued with ſenſible qualities, and contain in them the formality of ſenſibility. But ſince to every acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is required corporeal contaction, and the object is very often at a large diſtance beyond the line of contiguity, removed from the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorium: it is no idle quaerie, by what manner, and by what medium, the object doth, beyond it ſelfe, invade the Organ? Our ſolution ſhall be the ſober reſolution of moſt heads of Mediocrity, that it is done by certain emanations and inviſible raies, carrying with them the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, ſimulachra, or repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſenſible objects, from which they are emitted. For ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble objects are not reſtrained only to the poverty and courſe operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of reall and materiall, but are enriched with the finer endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſpiritual and intentional qualities: which are nothing, but the purer images of themſelves, by ſubtle radiation, and tenuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued effluviums flowing from themſelves; and that there are ſuch
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170136:57"/>ſpiritual effluxions we cannot deny, unleſs we make invalid the chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement of belief, our experience; for in ſummer, when to contempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the aeſtuation of the Suns per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular embraces, we ſecure our ſelves in the gentle refrigerium and ſolace of the Groves (the beſt &amp; moſt natural Vmbradoes) &amp; recreate us by accubation, under verdant Arbors, if we wil but take the pains to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, we ſhal ſee our garments apparently infected with the green tincture of the ſupereminent leaves; and if we place a white linnen cloth, or fine white paper, collateral to a Venice-glaſſe, filled with Claret-wine, it will, in apparition, wear the crimſon Livery of your wine: and many other examples (many whereof are enumerated by <hi>Scaliger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Et in genere Artificialia ſpecula hoc de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, quae ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines viſibiles etiam diſſitarum rerum recipiunt.</note> 
                  <hi>Exercitat</hi> 80. <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. <hi>et exercit.</hi> 298. <hi>S.</hi> 3.) do with Autoptical teſtimony eſtabliſh, that the intentional qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, or repreſentative formes of ſenſibles, are by emanation, from their groſſer materials, delivered at a diſtance.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſenſibles,<note place="margin">Senſibilia:</note> in this abſtracted
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170136:58"/>notion accepted,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Propria.</note> are (1.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> which fall under the compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of one ſolitary ſenſe, and hold no relation to any other; thus lucid and colorated objects are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to perception only of the ſight; ſounds are the buſineſſe only of the hearing, Sapors only affect the Guſto or taſt, Odors the ſmel; and Tangi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles concern only the Touch. (2.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Common,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Communia.</note> which are perceptible by all, or moſt ſenſes; ſuch are Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure Magnitude, Number, Motion, and Quieſcence.</p>
               <p>The laſt coadjutor is a Medium,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Medium. Lib. de Anima. cap. <hi>11.</hi> text. <hi>114:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; de An. cap. <hi>9.</hi> text <hi>89.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> which <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſeduced by the concurrents to, &amp; manner of viſion, by an infirm illation from a plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to an univerſality, concludes of uncontrollable neceſſity to all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But, under favour of ſo mighty a Prince of knowledge, this aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though by undenyable truth it hold good in viſion; and by proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble explication may be maintained in hearing, and ſmelling; yet how it can be made out in the touch, and taſt, to which is required an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate contact and corporeall impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170136:58"/>of the objects on their proper ſenſoriums, ſeems no eaſie problem, and threatens deſpaire of determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the boldeſt inquiry.</p>
               <p>Concerning that grand queſtion with ſo much ardor of contention,<note place="margin">An ſenſio ſit tantum paſſio; an vero etiam actio?</note> banded betwixt the ſurly diſciples of <hi>Plato,</hi> and the more paſſionate ſcholars of <hi>Aristotle; An ſenſio ſit tantum paſſio; an verò etiam actio?</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſion be a meer paſſion, and nothing more then the bare recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſenſible ſpecies; or whether beſids this admiſſion, there be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired alſo an action done by the ſenſator? We conceive it the duty of our method to ſuperſede the nauſeous enumeration of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are planted by each faction, to defend their own, and batter the adverſaries opinion, and only to preſent that poſitive and veriſimilous aſſertion, which may beſt deſerve our aſſent: And this is it, that the object emitting the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible image, or imaginary Idea, is not the agent, or active principium of ſenſion, but doth by tender, and oblation of the ſenſible ſpecies,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170136:59"/>objectively move the ſenſe.<note place="margin">Dari <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> naturales ſuadere id vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hoc; quod aliqui, quoties volunt, abſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem &amp; aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem mentis a Corpore pati poſſint. Cardan. de Variet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rerum &amp; de ſeipſo, &amp; Facio patre id teſtatur, ac quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vellent, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis ſic abreptos ſcribit, ut nullum omninò dolorem in eo ſtatu ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirent. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de Civit. Dei <hi>lib. 14. cap. 24.</hi> Simile quid narrat de quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam preſbytero, &amp;c. Et Anima aliis rebus ita intenta eſse po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, ut ſpeciem viſibilem etiam oculo praeſentem, &amp; vocem aures circumſonan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, oculo &amp; aure ſana non percipiat.</note> Neither can ſenſation be juſtly defined to be onely a paſſive reception, as may be evidenced by this, that very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, although the ſenſibles are paſſively admitted into the Organ, yet is not the Organ actively dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into ſenſation, when the ſoule in a naturall Extaſie withdrawes her ſelf from the diſtraction of the ſenſe, and neglects the Cognition of objects: but is alſo a determinate action performed by the Senſator: whoſe dignity wee ſhall highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage, to deny it the prime activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in its own proper buſineſſe. More briefly thus; the ſoul ſo farre forth as it diſcernes, and gives judgement of the objects, may, with ſafety of reaſon, be ſaid to be active: but ſo far forth as the ſpecies are conveyed to the ſenſe, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the Organs, in which the ſoul affectively reſides, it may, without danger of abſurdity, be affirmed to be paſſive.</p>
               <p>That the Externall ſenſes exceed not the number of five,<note place="margin">Senſus Externi &amp; tantum.</note> is the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Philoſophy, as uncontroll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170136:59"/>as generall; for five invincible reaſons: for in Natures wide Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitheatre, the Univerſe, are ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but five ſimple bodies (and, for ought we know, no diſtraction ever fell on ſo wild an Alogy, and groſs abſurdity, as to dream of more) the Heaven and the four Elements; to which the ſenſes by familiar analogy correſpond; the ſight (if we admit the doctrine of the ſober Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks) claimes Kindred of the ſtarrs, for its object is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhining and not burning; the ſmell reſembles the fire, for all Aromaticks confeſſe an Empyreuma and large participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Element, and therefore <hi>Fragrantia, quaſi Flagrantia,</hi> is more then a Grammarians Etymology; the hearing, by relation to its object, which is Aëriall, is allyed to the Aer; the Taſt, for the ſame reaſon, is cozen German once removed to the Water; and laſtly, the object of the Touch derives it ſelf from the dominion of Earth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the great All (that is ſo much as lies in the narrow ſphear of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man comprehenſion) are diſcovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170136:60"/>but five proper objects, <hi>viz.</hi> Colours, Sounds, Odors, Sapors, &amp; Tactile Qualities, and who will find more muſt gt out of <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> Circle, and hunt on the outſide of the world for them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Mediums required to the production of ſenſion, are capable of alteration and prediſpoſition but by five waies; which we muſt (ſuch is the command of our method) with induſtry forget, and referr the diſquiſition of our friends to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive plenary determination from <hi>Ariſt. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Anima.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. There are no more, nor leſſe then five ſenſes neceſſary, <hi>ad Eſſe &amp; benè Eſſe vitae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Experience, the grand induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our knowledge (on which we may moſt ſafely erect determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) witneſſeth that no diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hath or can point out more then five Organs, either in man, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the perfection, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the norma or rule of all ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary creatures, or in any other Animal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170136:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Sight.</head>
               <p>HAving thus with temerity crowded through the conflux of Generalls, wee are admitted to particulars: and the ſenſe, which (deſervedly) firſt arreſt the eye of our obſervation, is the ſight. For although that immortall controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie betwixt the two grandees in the common-wealth of learning, the Philoſopher and the Phyſician (two happy ſtarrs in conjunction, but oppoſed, they portend a deluge of Barbariſme) whether is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent the ſight or touch, depend in aequilibrio; yet have we thought it no impeachment to our profeſſion, to ſide with the Philoſopher, and vote for the primacy of the ſight, as by unqueſtionable right, and the prerogative of Natures bounty, properly belonging to it, witneſſe theſe ſubſequent conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This demonſtrats to us more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and differences of objects then
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170136:61"/>any other ſence; for all (at leaſt moſt) bodies appear clad either in the livery of ſome one ſingle colour, or in a variegated and verſicolor dreſſe, and ſo fal under the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the ſight, but not of the touch.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides its own proper object, it runs (with unlimited commiſſion) through all the common ones, and ſurveyes the Figure, Magnitude, Number, Motion, Site, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of each viſible; ſo that from hence ſhould any derive the pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of all Arts and Sciences, and affirm that from this Divine ſence, as from the protoplaſt, all honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inventions (thoſe aërial ones of Muſick excepted) have received their fruitful productions, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive multiplications: we confeſſe we could not diſallow the probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Genealogy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Viſion is performed by a moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſwifter then that of ill-ſpent time, &amp; even at the remoteſt diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; &amp; for this reaſon, ſhould we chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter the ſight to be the ſhaddowes or repreſentative reflex of the ſoul, as
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170136:61"/>that is of Divinity, the reſemblance would be our warrant; for as this comprehends the Idea's of things, exalted above the contagion of their materials, ſo that admits the incorporeal and intentional images of the objects: as the one is capable of two contraries, at one and the ſame inſtant of time, and diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth betwixt true and falſe; ſo the other at once diſcernes white and black, and while it receives one contrary, is not hindered from the perfect dignotion of the other: the intellect enjoyes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and arbitrary power of electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reſolution, which ſubmits to no compulſion; the ſight in its action is uncontrolled, and boaſts a liberty, which the indulgence of nature hath conferr'd upon it, but denyed to the younger brethren, the other ſenſes; for the ears ſtand ever open to the admiſſion of ſounds, and the noſtrils have no guard, but what they borrow from the hand, to protect them from the incurſion of ingrateful and offenſive odors; but the eyes are fortifyed
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170136:62"/>with counter-ſcarfs, or curtains, wherewith, at pleaſure, they may repulſe the invaſion of the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive object.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſight by its <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, exquiſite and infaillible dignotion, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, contributes more to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence; for a Canon it is in the Civil Law, worn into a proverb, <hi>plus valet oculatus teſtis, quam auriti de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem,</hi> the teſtimony of one eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe carries more aſſurance and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, then of ten that aſſume their information from the eare. From theſe and other reaſons of equal perſwaſive validity, we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to deduce the error of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophrastus,</hi> who miſtook the ſight, for the eſſence of man, and that laps of <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> who affirmed that viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was the prime end of our creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>How wonderful are the works of thy hands,<note place="margin">Viſus elogium.</note> Oh Lord! were but the Perſian learned in the Opticks, how ſoon would he become this ſenſes Proſelyte, with bluſhes red as his angry deity, forgoe his fond Idolatry of the Sun, and addreſſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170136:62"/>his more pardonable devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the more glorious Luminary, the Eye, wherein the image of Divinity is far more reſplendent; for the Sun irradiates the world. yet without comfort or benefit to it ſelfe; but the bright Gemini of the leſſer world, do not only illuminate the body, but inform and delight themſelves in the beauty they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover: When the Sun goes down to wake the Antipodes, and leaves our Hemiſphear benegro'd, we can delude the Tyranny of Night with Tapers, and kindle an artificiall day; but when once our own lights ſuffer extinction, what an eternal blackneſs ſurrounds us? from which no beams, but thoſe of the Sun of glory, can relieve us, &amp; which, in this life is an affliction, that anticipats the horid opacity of the Grave. and had not the purblind Soul of <hi>Momus</hi> been more ignorant, then his calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would have made Nature ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, he had diſcovered thoſe win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows in the eyes, which his blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my proclaimed deficient in the compoſure of man; or according
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170136:63"/>to the charracter given them by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the <hi>Pertpatetick,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mirantur Ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, a lamant, concupiſcunt, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris, irae, furo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, miſericordiae ultionis indices ſunt; in audacia proſiliunt; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentia ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, in amore blandiuntur, in dio efferantur, gaudente: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo hilares ſubſident, in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitatione ac cura quieſcunt, quaſi cum mente ſimul intenti, &amp;c. <hi>Laur.</hi> Lib. de Senſ. Org. <hi>11. Cap. 3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they are the mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Soul, wherein all her clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet conceptions, whether peaceful or paſſionate, are written in the ſpiritual alphabet of looks, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitively legible; witneſſe the mute intelligence of Lovers, who can converſe like Angels, and conceive each other by glances, that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficantly deliver their apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and carry with them the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and contents of their deſires.</p>
               <p>But we reduce our pen (that had not wanderd, but in hope to have met with ſome encomium, that might have run parralel to the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this learned ſenſe, and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated the digreſſion) back from this licentious ſeduction, and chain it to the definitive expreſſions of more ſevere Philoſophy.</p>
               <p>The ſight is an exterior ſenſe,<note place="margin">Viſus <hi>1.</hi> Difinitio. <hi>2.</hi> Organon.</note> that receives and diſcernes external viſible objects, by the miniſtration or benefit of the eye, which is the adaequate organ of viſion.</p>
               <p>This leſſer microcoſme, the eye,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170136:63"/>is the inſtrument of ſight,<note place="margin">Oculi.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of ſix Muſcles, three (the externall and conjunctive except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) Coats or Membranes, three Humors, two Nerves, very many Veins and Arteries, and a large quantity of Fat: Of theſe parts, we ſhall only meet with ſo many as immediately are officiall to viſion, and the firſt that among them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes our obſervation, is the <hi>Cornea Tunica,</hi> Horny Membrane.</p>
               <p>This coat, being originally a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Corea Tuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> or proceſſe of the <hi>Dura meninx,</hi> and enſhrining the whole eye, wears the Epithites <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Corneous and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hard, from the manifeſt ſimilitude betwixt it and a Horn, ſhaved to a tranſparent thinneſſe; for in ſubſtance it is (1.) perſpicuous or tralucid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Perſpicua.</note> that the viſible ſpecies may have admiſſion or tranſitus into the eye. (2.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> void of all colour, that the images may permeate into the eye, clad in their native purity, and not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed with the infection of any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour but their own: (3.) hard,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Durus</note> that it may the better oppoſe exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170136:64"/>injuries: (4.) denſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Denſa.</note> that the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>images after progreſſion through a thinner medium, the Aer arriving on a thicker medium, this Membra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne may be refracted; for we are to obſerve in general, that ſince viſion is made by refraction, and refracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made for the variety of the diaphanum; that all parts of the eye, that are immediately inſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſight, do performe their office as they are tralucide and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, and differ in diaphanity according to their tenuity and thickneſſe. The figure of this coat is round,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Rotunda.</note> that the eye might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern objects greater then it ſelfe. <hi>Si enim Oculus non eſſet rotundus, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titati rei capiendae non ſufficerit. Vid. Perſpect. Comm. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>propoſ.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>Between this Membrane and the Chryſtalline Humor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Humor Aqueus.</note> is lodged a liquid ſubſtance, called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Aqueous, or Albugineous Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, which is ordained diaphanous, and void of all colour, for the ſame reaſons the Horny coat is ſo, and more rare then it, that here the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies may ſuffer a ſecond refraction.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170136:64"/>
               <p>This liquor effuſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Vuea Tunica.</note> the next conſiderable that occurs, is the ſecond coat, called <hi>fo</hi> the the grapy Tunicle,<note place="margin">Verſicolor.</note> from the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance in colour and ſuperficies it holds with the kernel of a grape, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe as the Chorion, it receives and ſupports the diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the Veſſells, which is a production of the <hi>Pia Mater,</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately inveſting the Optick Nerve, expanſed into a membrane. This, of all parts of the eye, onely is <hi>diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>color;</hi> for on the outſide, where it toucheth on the horny Coat, it bears ſables (a colour not to be found in any other part of the body, if <hi>Galens</hi> inquiſition ſatisfie, <hi>Lib. de uſu part.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.) on the inſide, where it faceth the Aqueous and Chriſtalline Humors, it is of a dark grey,<note place="margin">Nigredinis uſus</note> or duskiſh brown, inclining to black; but where it conſtituteth the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Circle Iris, or the Rainbow, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears ſometimes skycoloured, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times green, and very often black.<note place="margin">Luces debiles in locis obſcurit magis apparent, in luminoſis latent.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the black tincture of this Coat, in that part, that reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Chryſtalline Humor, Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170136:65"/>and the maſters of the opticks agree, that Nature intended it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the Chryſtalline Humor being herewith veiled over; might the better recollect and congregate his own brightneſſe, for, according to the poſition of <hi>Alhazen. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>prop.</hi> 33. a ſmall light in a dark obſcure place is better perceptible, and diffuſes a brighter luſtre, then in a wide, light place, and makes the circumjacent parts more viſible; ſo the internall ſplendor of the eye becomes more bright, and the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble images appeare more illuſtrious in the Chryſtalline Humor, becauſe the inner circumference of the whole eye is lined with this dark and obſcure membrane, by whoſe ſhadow the Chryſtalline is eclipſed; ſo that his refulgent brightneſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting back from the oppoſite opa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the membrane, is aſſembled and united in a more vigorous luſtre: or for the collection, recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and refection of the viſive ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; for when the Chryſtalline is offended by a too vehement light, we for remedy cloſe our eyes, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170136:65"/>the ſpirits recoyling back upon this naturall darkneſſe of the Coat, are reaſsembled and refreſhed; or for the interception of light, for ſince the anterior perforation of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py coat, is the only portal, built and deſtined to the immiſſion of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible images; and there ought to be no ſecond paſſage, whereby the light might intrude it ſelfe, what could Nature more conveniently have thought on to exclude the light, then the interjection of this black curtain when experience hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it an Axiome, that nothing better intercepts and ſhuts out light, then the interpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of opace bodies.<note place="margin">Iridis uſus.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But concerning the main intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Nature, in her embrodery of this Coat (in that part, which look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth outward, and makes the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coloured rainbow) with ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of dies,<note place="margin">Iris oritur exin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, quod uvee Tunicae limbus varios colores habet.</note> and whether ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived it either for neceſſary uſe (which is moſt probable) or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ornament; we find the Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of Oculiſts rather amazed,<note place="margin">Pupilla.</note> then their diſquiſitions ſatisfied. Wherefore wee think it ſafe for us
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170136:66"/>to fix on nothing, but a ſcepticall neutrality; and to acquieſce in no other reſolution, then to ſit down, and modeſtly expect the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of future diſcovery.</p>
               <p>In the forepart of this membrane is a ſmall Foramen or perforation, through which the viſible images ae intromitted to the Chryſtalline, called the Pupilla, which vulgarity tranſlates the Apple of the Eye, the narrow circumference of this (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively to that of the Chryſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, or Cornea) principally condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to the perfection and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of viſion:<note place="margin">Dilatatio &amp; Contractio.</note> yet in many the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude varies; and thoſe in whom Nature hath framed it very narrow, are quick and acute ſighted: but thoſe who have it more dilated, ſee but weakly and obtuſely.</p>
               <p>This Apple of the Eye is daily Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anguſted and dilated, and appeares much more coarctated in a lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, then in an obſcure crepuſculous place; For ſince an Exceſſe of light is deſtructive, and the defect of it inſufficient to viſion: the Eternall wiſdom hath, in the very entrance
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170136:66"/>of the Eye, contrived this window capable of dilatation and contracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: in dilatation to admit ſo much of the weaker light as is required to perfect and diſtinct viſion:<note place="margin">Dilatationis Cauſa.</note> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction to exclude ſo much of the copious and exceſſive, as would either offend, or periſh the Organ.</p>
               <p>When we enquire the cauſe of this dilatation, Common and popular Philoſophy referrs us to the Animal Spirit; and believes that the Apple of one Eye is dilated when the other Eye is cloſed, becauſe of the conflux, and congregation of all the viſive ſpirits into the open Eye: But this doth not ſatisfie our ſcrutiny, ſince though both eyes are open, yet wee plainly diſcover this dilatation and Contraction. For (according to the annotation of <hi>Io. Bap. Porta Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de refract. cap.</hi> 6. and the confeſſion of <hi>Hieron. Fabricius ab Aquapendente. Lib. de viſion.</hi> part 3. c. 6.) if we look into the Eyes of any opened againſt the Sun, we cannot but perceive the Pupilla to be ſo ſtraightly coan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtated, that there will appear hardly room enough to admit the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170136:67"/>point of a needle. The learned <hi>Scheg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kius,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Spirit. Animal.</hi> teacheth us, that the Foramen of the <hi>Uvea tunica</hi> is ampliated and wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Contraction of Muſcles in the root of the Eye, which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately invirons the optick Nerve: but contracted by the relaxation of the ſame; for the Coates ſeem ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in the Extream or root of the Eye. And, in our approbation, this weighs heavieſt in the ballance of Truth.</p>
               <p>This admirable conſtitution of the <hi>Uvea</hi> occaſioneth thoſe three naturall degrees,<note place="margin">Gradus viſionis.</note> or graduall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of our Sight;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Perfectiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> (1.) <hi>Viſus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiſſimus in indiviſibili conſtitutus,</hi> when we, with the exquiſite diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction diſcern <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> minute atomicall bodies:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Perfectus.</note> (2.) <hi>perfectus,</hi> when, at a proportionate diſtance, we diſtinctly ſee the object, but not apprehend the minimum, the ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt particle of each:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Confuſus.</note> (3.) <hi>imperfectus,</hi> when, beſides thoſe objects, which are <hi>è directo</hi> oppoſed, we alſo have a confuſed and glimmering apparition of other; placed <hi>ad latera,</hi> on the right, or left hand.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170136:67"/>
               <p>The cauſe of which difference is thus made out;<note place="margin">Graduum viſus cauſa.</note> ſince the comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the viſible image is made <hi>per pyramidem,</hi> by an acute angle; but the Certification is made <hi>per Axem,</hi> by a direct line; and onely that perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular radius, which is called the <hi>Axis,</hi> and is not refracted, doth powerfully and diſtinctly repreſent the object; but all other <hi>oblique radij,</hi> by how much they are nearer unto, or removed from the Axis, are by ſo much the more, or leſſe efficacious and conducible to repreſentation. Hence comes it, that when the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilla is contracted to a ſmaller cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference; onely the direct and perpendicular radius in the viſive Pyramid enters to the Center of the Chryſtalline, or together with it thoſe radij which are neareſt to the Axis: but when it is dilated, many other oblique and refracted beams, ruſh together with the perpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicular, and confuſe the viſion. And the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous experiment of<note n="*" place="margin">Dyonyſius upra carcerem tenibricoſum, domum extruxit lucidiſſimam, clariſſimam, calce illitam; &amp; homines carcere obſcuro diu concluſos, ex profundis tenebris in lucem ſplendi-diſſimam Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo occaeavit.</note> 
                  <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> the Sicilian Prodigy, hath with learned tyranny confirmed, that if the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilla, when it is dilated, be ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="6 pages">
                     <desc>〈6 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:170136:68"/>
               <p>of <hi>Plato's</hi> Jubilee) apply themſelves to every viſible, &amp; hold a voluntary verticity to the object. <hi>Parvula ſic magnum perviſit pupula Coelum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of theſe ocular Muſcles there are in man juſt ſo many, as there are motions, four direct, and two circular, all ſituated within the cavity of the ſcul, and accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Optick Nerve, and all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning their tendons, at the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, do conſtitute the nameleſſe Tunicle, ſo named by <hi>Columbus,</hi> as if it had eſcaped the obſervation of the antient Anatomiſts;<note place="margin">Galen. L. <hi>10.</hi> de uſu partium. cap. <hi>2. 1.</hi> Attollens.</note> s when (in truth) it had not the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of <hi>Galen</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt of thoſe implanted in the ſuperior part of the eye, and draweth it upward, whence it is called <hi>Attollens,</hi> the lifter up; and <hi>ſuperbus,</hi> the proud; for this we uſe in haughty and ſublime looks.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſituated in the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior part,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Deprimens.</note> is Antagoniſt to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and ſtoops the eye down to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the cheek, and from this is called <hi>Deprimens,</hi> the depreſſor, and <hi>Humilis,</hi> the humble Muſcle, for this poſition of the eye ſpeaks the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170136:68"/>dejection and humility of the mind.</p>
               <p>The third ſeated in the <hi>Major Canthus,</hi> or angle of the eye,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Adducens.</note> and leading it toward the Noſe is called <hi>Adducens et Bibitorius,</hi> for in large draughts we often contractit.</p>
               <p>The opponent to this is the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in the minor Angle,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Abducens.</note> which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the eye <hi>ad latera,</hi> therefore called <hi>Abducens et indignatorius;</hi> for when we would look with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and indignation, we by the contraction of this Muſcle, hale the eye into an oblique and ſcornful poſition.</p>
               <p>If all theſe four work together, the eye is drawn inward, fixed, and eſtabliſhed; which kind of motion Phyſicians call <hi>motus Tonicus,</hi> we in our language, the Set, or wiſt-look.</p>
               <p>The fift ſlender oblique Muſcle,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Obliquus.</note> running betwixt the eye, and the tendons of the ſecond and third Muſcles, by the outward angle, aſcends to the ſuperior part of the eye, and inſerted neer to the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, circumgyrats the eye down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>The laſt, and ſmalleſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6.</hi> Trochiea.</note> twiſted
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170136:69"/>into a long Tendon circumrotates the Eye towards the interior angle, and is called the Trochlea Muſcle or pully. Theſe two circumactors are ſurnamed <hi>Amatorij</hi> the Lovers Muſcles, for theſe are they that wheele about the Eye in wanton or amorous glances.<note place="margin">Objectum viſus.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Although our reaſon embrace for a verity, that admits no dubitation, that the object of Sight is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Viſible, in generall whatever ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to the comprehenſion of the Sight; and in particular, that the proper and adaequate object of this ſence is Colour; for nothing is viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but under the gloſs and verniſh of Colour, nay, Light it ſelf (which ſome entertein for the ſecond object of viſion (ſubmits not to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment of the Eye, <hi>quatenus Lux,</hi> under the notion of its own forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but <hi>inſtar albedinis,</hi> as it retaines to whiteneſſe: yet when it attempts an eſtabliſhed and ſatisfactory the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory of the true nature of Colours; it ſoon runns to a ſtand, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers nothing of more certainty, then that this jewell, the knowledge of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170136:69"/>the nature of colours, is only digged out by the miners after Knowledge, but no hand was ever yet ſo happy as to be conſtellated to the Exantla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or landings of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the ſubtle Genius of Nature <hi>Lib de ſenſu &amp; ſenſili. cap.</hi> 3. defines Colours to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the extremity of a diapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num terminated; and ſubjoines, that Colours belongs to al things <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione perſpicuitatis,</hi> and that the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanum or pellucid body termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; is the ſubject of Colour; For if the <hi>perſpicuum</hi> ſuffer condenſation to the amiſſion of its tranſparency, and ſo forbid the tranſmiſſion of the viſible ſpecies, it become coloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and may be ſaid to be termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for it preſcirbes bounds and limits unto the ſight, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the act of viſion: And thus aſcribes the Cauſes of Colour unto the graduall termination of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphanum; which proceeds (1.) from the condenſation of the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanum alone, without the admiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any other body; thus ſtarrs being lucid bodies compacted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170136:70"/>viſible: (2.) from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtion of an opace, with a tralucent body, thus Fire, in the primitive ſimplicity of its own nature moſt perſpicuous, appears red, becauſe commixt; and obnubilated with fumes and exhalations,<note place="margin">De colorum commistione, &amp; ſpeciebus, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta egregiè ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit Scalig. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitation. <hi>325.</hi>
                  </note> and thus from the concorporation and mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Element with another, of a lucid and tranſparent with an opace and terreſtrious, come forth the primitive and ground colours; and from the various and complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unition of theſe firſt and father extream colours, all other interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and changable tinctures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their originall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others refer the cauſes of prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſecundary Colours to the graduality of opacity and light.</p>
               <p n="3">And the Chymiſts (who in their laborious exploration have out done all other in this abſtruſity) reduce their cauſes unto <hi>Sal, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> and believe that bodies receive luſtre or obſcurity, and by ſequell, the various degrees of colours, from the various mixture of their volatile with their fixt ſalt.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:170136:70"/>
               <p>But from neither, not all of theſe opinions ariſeth, to a ſubtle exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſatifaction enough to termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate our Enquirie; or to accuſe us of ſingularity, if (in this particular) we appear ſcepticall, and profeſſe to ſuſpend our adhaerence to authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, untill it ſhall, with leſſe obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, attempt the revelation of this Magnale.</p>
               <p>The Medium of Sight is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Perſpicuum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Medium viſus.</note> all bodies qualified with pellucidity or perſpicuity: and the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath more opacity then the Medium. Hence is one Element perceptible in another, water in Aer, and Earth in water; and the ſame colorated thing is conſpicuous in pure and limpid water; but invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in turbid and polluted. And for this reaſon a colourated object may be a Medium, provided, that it be not abſolutely opace, but more tralucent then the viſible. For thus <hi>Braſſavolus</hi> ſaw his Piſmire, and <hi>Cardan</hi> his Silkworm, through the diaphanous ſolidity of their Electri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Mauſoleums.</p>
               <p>That Viſion was doen by Emiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Modus Viſionis.</note> and that the Optick ſpirits did
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170136:71"/>in a continued viſive radius ſtream from the Eye to the object, and ſo apprehend it; was an error of no meaner Extraction, then the great Patriarch of the ſtoicks, and adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the patronage of all Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, that ſpent that long inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall of time, betwixt him and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> but exiled by the juſtice of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> reaſon, it for ever reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the poſſeſſion of the Schools, to the juſt dominion of truth: and ſince few have been ſuch ſtubborn votaries to the tyranny of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as not to ſubſcribe the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that viſion is made by the reception of the viſible ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in to the Eye; and that neither <hi>radij,</hi> nor Light, nor Spirit, are emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Organ towards the object. The reaſons are moſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly recited by <hi>Jul. Caeſ. Scaliger, Exercit.</hi> 32 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 298. <hi>&amp;</hi> 289. Sect. ib. &amp;c. <hi>Zabar: Lib,</hi> 2. <hi>de viſu cap.</hi> 4.5. and <hi>Andr. Laur. Libr.</hi> 2. <hi>de ſens. Organ. Quaeſtione prima.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we look within our ſelves,<note place="margin">Finis viſionis.</note> and read the end and duty of our ſight, we cannot but conceive the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170136:71"/>Error of <hi>Anaxaggras Homines ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum eſſe natos,</hi> more veniall then that of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and moſt of his Pupils, <hi>viſum eſſe ſenſum Commodita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis;</hi> and could heartily wiſh he had ſaid <hi>Faelicitatis.</hi> For the beatitude of man is Eſſenced in the Knowledge and contemplative (though but graduall) comprehenſion of God; and no ſenſe ſo clearly manifeſt's the immenſe glory of the Creator, as this that is familiar with the beauty of the Creature. For though the Brutall part of mankind, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run with ſenſuality, think the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of their Creation ſatisfied in the actions of ſenſe, and ſeldome look beyond the barks and Exteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors of things: yet the Phioſopher extends his eye to inviſibility, being raviſhed with the borrowed glory of the viſible: and ſome have been beholding to their ſight for their Converſion, and happily confeſſed that the Eye of their ſenſe hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the acies of their reaſon to the eſſence of all eſſences, and ſoul of all cauſalities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:170136:72"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Hearing.</head>
               <p>'TWas a Hypochondriack ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity of <hi>Plato,</hi> that all our Cognition is but Recognition, and our acquired intellection, but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſcence, or reherſall of thoſe primitive leſſons the Soul had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, for proper Science is proper onely to Omniſcience, and not to receive knowledge by infuſion, or acquiſition, but to have it ſpring from the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain of his own eſſence, is the attribute onely of the Eſſence of wiſdom, and a priviledge due to none, but the Antient of daies, to have his knowledge deriv'd beyond Antiquity: but Man, poor ignorant Man, commanded into the World on the deſign of knowledge, muſt ſweat in the exploration and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of it; and can never poſſeſs any ſcience, in this life, but what hee muſt dearly purchaſe with his own diſcovery, or precariouſly borrow
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170136:72"/>from the bounteous induſtry of his Forefathers. Now that the mind of man might partake the notion of what concerns this,<note place="margin">Quemadmodum aſpectus ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae dulcedinem, &amp; commoda magis eſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarius, ita Auditus ad ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendam ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſapienti am &amp; ſcientiam eſt accommodatior. Ille ad inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, hic ad Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem aptior eſt Lauren. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> and the future life, his Creator hath furniſhed him with the ſenſe of Hearing; the ſenſe particularly and expreſly diſpoſed for Diſcipline, for though wee ſing Hymnes to the Eye for the inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet we muſt acknowledge a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice due to the Ear, for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and diſtribution of Arts and Sciences,. And this the Aegyptians intimate in their Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphick of memory, and the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher expreſſeth in his character of the Hearing, <hi>Auditus eſt ſenſus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciplinae:</hi> and the glory of our Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Sennertus</hi> elegantly delivers thus, <hi>Aures in Homine quaſi porta mentis ſunt, per quam menti communicantur, quae doctrina &amp; inſtitutione de Deo &amp; aliis rebus neceſſariis traduntur, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nullo alio ſenſu addiſci poſſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hearing is an Externall ſenſe receiving and perceiving <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> all ſounds audible,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Definitio.</note> by the benefit of the Ear.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Organum.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The adaequate inſtrument of
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170136:73"/>hearing is the Ear; divided by Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomiſts into the (1.) Externall, and (2.) Internall.</p>
               <p>The Externall Eare,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Auris Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note> or <hi>Auricula,</hi> (intended by <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in that prognoſtick, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Aures frigidae, pellu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidae, &amp; inverſae mortiferae</hi>) was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Nature (1.) for Ornament, (2.) for the refraction of the Aer, whoſe uncorrected violence and impetuoſity, would otherwiſe ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Tympanum or Drum-head; (3) to catch and collect the ſpecies of ſoundes diffuſed and ſcattered in the Aer, and through its unfractu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Convolutions convey them into the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or auditory ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. For thoſe that have loſt their externall Ears hear but obtuſely and confuſedly, and receive all ſounds and articulate voices, like the purling murmur of a rivulet, or the fritiniancy and ſhrill note of Graſhoppers. Hence Brute Animals, by the dictate of inſtinct prick up or arrect their ears in a poſition to meet and intercept the wandering ſounds; Hence <hi>Hadrian</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170136:73"/>to palliate his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate his imminution of this ſenſe,<note place="margin">Hinc exactius audiunt quibus aures exterius prominent, &amp; ſi non nimium, tam en longo decubitu, quam neutricum liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis, aures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsas habere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, rectius audiremus.</note> ſet his hands to his ears in a promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent poſture, with the palmes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and hence thoſe Scythians, whoſe outward ears are ſyderated or ſphacelated by extremity of cold, plant Cockle, or Schallop ſhells in their rooms, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and direction of the ſounds that preterlaps the <hi>Meatus Auditorius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The external Aer charged with the audible ſpecies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Auris inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note> and thus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and conducted by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Meatus audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius.</note> is wafted into the inward eare, through the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory Canale, which is a long, round, oblique perforation of the <hi>os petroſum,</hi> or ſtony bone, inveſted with a thin, denſe, hard, perpolite skin, that firmly adheres to the bone, that the ſound may herein ſuffer denſation, collection, and turbination. In this Cavity is found that bilious humor (called by <hi>Aegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neta</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſordiculas in auribus,</hi> and by the vulgar Engliſh, the eare-wax (or gluttinous expurgation of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170136:74"/>the brain,<note place="margin">Cicer. <hi>2.</hi> de Natur. Deorum ut ſi quae mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma beſtiola co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur irrumpore, in ſordibus his, tanquam in viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio nihaereſcat.</note> provided (if we reject not the conception of <hi>Cicero</hi>) for the inviſcation of the Auricularia Earewig, and other ſmall inſects.</p>
               <p>In the end of this Foramen is ſpread a tranverſe interſtitiary, or round parchment (called by ſome Anatomiſts the myrinx, by others the mediaſtinum,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Tympanum.</note> by moſt the Tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panum, but by the beſt the drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head) to exclude the external from ruſhing in, and concorporating with the internal or congenite Aer: for ſince the external Aer is ſubject to Anomalies, incraſſation, humecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and inquination; were it but admitted to a conjunction with the originary internal, it would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turb the native tenuity and purity thereof, and impoſe upon it the contagion of its own impreſſions. The ſubſtance of this partition is not oſſeous, leſt the ſounds ſhould be repulſed; nor carneous and ſoft, for that was abſolutely unapt for tranſmiſſion of the ſounds; but membranous and nervous; yet pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucid, thin, and ſubtile, that the ſounds may be intromitted to the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170136:74"/>ingenite Aer; for thoſe, who have this membrane incraſſated, and too much condenſed, from the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive conformation, ſuffer a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or deafneſſe incurable, and muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the attenuation and rarefaction of it, from the energy of no heat, but that of the Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which ariſeth with healing in his wings; and the dryeſt of any Membrane in the body, for the better reception of the ſounds: for dry &amp; hard bodies principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce both to the admiſſion and reſonation of ſounds; witneſſe our experiment in muſical inſtruments and the Aphoriſm of our Oracle; in his deſcription of the Tympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panum:<note place="margin">Hippocr. Lib. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> To <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> There is in the ear, neer to the rocky bone, a thin filme or tunicle, like the ſpiders web, and of all other membranes the dryeſt, but that, what hath moſt Siccity, is moſt apt to reſound, there are many Evidences.</p>
               <p>Behind this traverſe, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170136:75"/>cavity of the eare, are found the three ſmall bones,<note place="margin">Oſſicula tria.</note> 
                  <hi>Incus, Stapes,</hi> and <hi>Malleus,</hi> the Anvil, Stirrop, and Hammer, in probability, borrowing theſe appellations, rather from their Figure, then office: For ſince ſolid, compacted, and polit bodies are moſt accommodable to the impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, delation, and communication of ſounds, the ſoul of reaſon, the Creator framed theſe three bones, ſubſtantially very hard and ſolid, and ſuperficially perpolite, that by their durities, and laevity, the ſounds may be delated to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantate Aer; and contrived them naked &amp; uninveſted, for were they obducted with any ſofter involuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Sunt haec ofsa ſolidiſſima, ut reſonent; &amp; quod mirum eſt, eorum in puerulo, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſt, quae in ſene magnitudo. Andr. Laur. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> they would be inofficial to pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and the ſucceſſive trajection of ſounds: and for no other reaſon their dimenſions are the ſame in all conſtitutions, and their magnitude in an Infant, equal to that of thoſe in ful grown procerity.</p>
               <p>We ſhall here,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Aer implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus.</note> with reſolution, be guilty of the omiſſion of ſome parts in the ear, concerning whoſe uſe, Authors deliver more of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170136:75"/>then certitude, and rather betray our diſquiſition into the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity and wilderneſſe of opinion, then conduct our curioſity home to the point and unity of eſtabliſhed truth; and apply our perpenſion only to the implantat Aer, being a ſubject as full of obſcurity, as worthy the induſtry of the ſubtileſt exploration. For though all parts in the ear be neceſſary to audition, that the vitioſity or defect of any, induceth a depravement or aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the action of all: Yet it is an opinion vulgarly paſſant, derived as high as <hi>Plato,</hi> aſſented to by <hi>Galen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galen. <hi>7.</hi> de decret. Hippocrat. &amp; Platon. cap. <hi>5.</hi> Ariſt. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de An.</note> and confirmed by <hi>Ariſtotle, Aerem implantatum eſſe princeps auditus Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> that the Originary Aer is the precipuous inſtrument of hearing. For as to the reception of the viſible image is provided an internal fulgor <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, conſociable to the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, which ſhould <hi>propter ſimilitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſubſtantiae,</hi> with familiarity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the external: ſo alſo in the ear is there <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an aeriall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, generated of the moſt pure,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170136:76"/>and rarified portion of the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive materials, the ſeed and mater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall blood, which by reaſon of cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and ſimilitude of ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Sedes aëris im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantati.</note> doth welcome and embrace the delated ſpecies of ſounds. But to conclude on the place, and ſituation of this implantate Aer, ſeems a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of no ſmall abſtruſity: <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Capivaccius</hi> ſeats it in the expan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the auditory Nerve: <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angelus Picolomin Lect.</hi> 5. is poſitive, that it is pent in the extream Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, or inmoſt den, drilled in the <hi>os petroſum;</hi> and <hi>Hieron. Fabricius ab Aquapendente</hi> beleeves, that all the cavities, angles, and creeks of the internall ear (which otherwiſe had remained <hi>natural Groteſcos,</hi> and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vacuums) are poſſeſſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleted by the implantate Aer.</p>
               <p>We muſt not indubitate the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of this innate Aer, nor queſtion the veriſimility of the opinion, that it is included in the ſinus of the ear,<note place="margin">Vſus deris im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantati.</note> to ſymbolize with the external advenient Aer, and ſo invite, at leaſt, admit it: but that
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170136:76"/>the principal and judicatory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Audition, is Aer, we dare ſuſpect, and can produce warrant from no contemptible authority to deny: For <hi>Hercules Saxonia,</hi> and <hi>Andreas I aurentius,</hi> (men whoſe names are Antidote ſufficient againſt prejudice) account the implantate Aer, only for the internal medium, inſervant to the convoy, and tranſmiſſion of all ſounds, ſimple or articulate, into the true and proper Organ of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; and teach us, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couſtick Nerve, determined and expanſed in the extremity or cone of the Cochlea or Snayl-ſhell, is the approximate Senſorium of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: And <hi>Galen. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de cauſ. ſymptomatum. Cap.</hi> 3. leaves it for granted, that the prime inſtrument of the hearing is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the internal end or extremity of the conduit. For the implantate Aer is the receptory of the ſpecies au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible diſcharged from the external Aer, through the anfractus and ſinuous tortuoſities of the ear, and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170136:77"/>immediately transfers them to the auditory Nerve, which is an exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus or production from the fifth conjugation of the brain, running through the perforation of the <hi>os petroſum</hi> into the ear, and there by a particular conſtitution, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and continued for the ſpeciall and determinate comprehenſion of Audibles. And a Catholic Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem it is, ſworn to by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> 2. <hi>de Anima. Nihil expers Animae ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cujus ſenſus eſt inſtrumentum;</hi> but this innate Aer partakes not animation;<note place="margin">Vid. Andr. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de ſens. Organ. Quaest. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> for the Soul is not <hi>actus corporis ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicis,</hi> but <hi>Organici;</hi> wherefore it cannot be the immediate Organ, but the internal medium of audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, generated of the ambient Aer, not by concoction and elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as are the Spirits, nor there by any action of the Soul, but by the perpetual arival of new Aer; which is partly tranſcolated through the Tympanum, and ſo delated into the Cochlea or Snayl-ſhell; and partly derived thither through the ſlender perforation
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170136:77"/>or pipe opening into the Palate. Hence may we reſolve that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem, why oſcitation or yawning perturbs our Hearing? For in oſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the expulſive Faculty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to diſcharge a dull va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour lodged in the cranies and chinks of the throat, which ariſing in compreſſion of the parts, unto the ears, by thoſe Foramina, made from them into the palate, croudes into the Snayl-ſhell, and cauſes a tonitruating and tumultuary noiſe, which drownes, or adulterates the calmer and more delicate ſpecies of ſounds offered from without.</p>
               <p>The external medium of this ſenſe is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Perſonabile,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Medium exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> Aer and Water: Both which elements (though <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> deafe unto the experiment of nocturnal piſcation, would not hear of the latter) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in their efficiencies, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute their faculties to Audition, in more then a ſingle reſpect, (1.) as a medium qualified both for the reception, and tranſvection: (2.) as materials neceſſary to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170136:78"/>of ſoundes. For in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion, the Faculty of the Medium, or potentia of the Materiall, is actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, when it is intercepted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacerated betwixt two ſolid bodies, vehemently charging each other. And a ſound is a quality produced from Aer,<note place="margin">Objectum Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> or Water percuſſed and fracted by the ſuddain, and violent concuſſion or arietation of ſolid bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Hence is it manifeſt to the capacity of any head, that was not conſtellated to ignorance, that to the generation or a ſound, is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the conſpiration and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of three concomitant, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſucceſſive Actions (1.) the affront, or ſhock of two ſolid bodies: (2.) the Eliſion or diſruption of the Medium (3.) the reſonance of the Medium; after which, immediately ſucceeds the ſound.</p>
               <p>The manner of this laceration, the moſt Elegant <hi>Julius Caſſerius Placentinus</hi> delivers thus.<note place="margin">Fractionis Modus.</note> When two ſolid bodies ſtrike one againſt the other, the intermediate body is with ſuch impetuoſity impulſed,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170136:78"/>that the Atomical parts of it cannot obſerve the order of motion by ſucceſſion one after another; but rather diſorderly throng and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent each other, before the firſt part hath avoided the place, another is driven upon the neck of it, and ſo the motion, which when ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed, is gentle and eaſie, becomes, by reaſon of this inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate impetuoſity, tumultuary and tempeſtuous. Hence is it that ſoft and acute bodies yeeld no ſound in their colliſion, becauſe the ſtroke betwixt them doth not ſo diſparkle or ſhatter the intermediate body, that thereon ſhould follow any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation or fraction, whereby the calme and ſucceſſive diſſipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or yeelding may be preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>The Externall Aer,<note place="margin">Audiendi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> thus qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the impreſſion of a ſound, alters the next adjoyning Aer, and this impells and alters the next to that, and ſo ſucceſſively untill <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> contiguity and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation it arrive at the ear; For as
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170136:79"/>on the injection of a ſtone into wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there will ariſe circles on the ſurface of the water, enlarging and purſuing each other: ſo from the eliſion of Aer, are there generated inviſible aeriall circles, moving in ſucceſſive rounds, or vocall waves, untill they attain unto the Organ of Hearing. But this undulation is not diſpatched in a moment, but in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of time. And for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a ſound is not preſently after the ſtroke delivered to places at diſtance: we behold the Coruſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nitrous and ſulphurous exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, fired in the Clouds, ſome minutes before wee hear the fragor given upon laceration: and wee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the flaſh, a good ſpace of time, before wee hear the report of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non: and in the open field we plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive the arme of a man, hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wood, lifted up for the ſecond ſtroak, before wee have heard the firſt.</p>
               <p>The Aer thus impregnated with a ſound, conducted and conglomera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Externall ear, firſt ſtrikes
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170136:79"/>upon the moſt dry, and reſounding membrane the Drum-head; this thus ſtrucken, juſtles and impells the three ſmall bones, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the Character of the ſound on them: they immediately glance it forwards to the implantate Aer: this ſhoots it through the windowes of the ſtony bone, into the winding Burroughs; thence wafts it into the Labyrinth; thence into the ſnail-ſhell, and at laſt ſurrenders it to the Acouſtick Nerve, which preſently tranſmit it to the Common ſenſe, as unto the Cenſor or Judge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:170136:80"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the Smell.</head>
               <p>THis is the middle Finger in the left hand of the ſenſitive Soul, and like vertue, dwells in <hi>Medio,</hi> between the other four, whoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſtand farther removed from mediocrity; For the Sight and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring extend their comprehenſion to the largeſt remove of proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate diſtance, and can arreſt the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject without the line of their owne ſituation: The Taſt, and Touch work not, but by contaction, and are not active beyond the narrow Orbe of corporall Contaction, and ſubſtantiall admotion: But the ſmell, whoſe nature is a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the others contrary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes, and a power in which are united the oppoſite impoſſibilities of the reſt, is actuated into appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, partly by the interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a medium, and partly by the contiguity and approximity of the object.</p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:170136:80"/>
               <p>Wee may therefore define Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be the middle ſenſe of the five externall,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Definitio:</note> which perceives the Odors of things drawn in by the noſtrills to the mamillary proceſſes of the brain, for the uſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of the Creature.</p>
               <p>That the Object of Smelling is an Odour,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Objectum.</note> is a univerſall Theorem oraculouſly eſtabliſhed beyond the deniall of any: but what the nature of an Odour is, hath been a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Problem, myſteriouſly removed above the comprehenſion of moſt. <hi>Heraclitus</hi> cited by <hi>Ariſtotle Lib. de ſens. &amp; ſenſili. cap.</hi> 5. many of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Philoſophers, and moſt of the Family of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> have left on record, for an indubitable max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime, that the ſmell is not affected only with an incorporeall quality, or ſpirituall ſpecies: but that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain aerial, ſubtile ſubſtance, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a vaporous exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is expired from the Odorate Object, which doth ſubſtantially move the ſenſe: and <hi>Galen. de instrum. Olfactus cap.</hi> 2. (though the Charity
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170136:81"/>of <hi>Caſſerius Placentinus</hi> attempts a witty vindication of ſo honorable a judgement from the guilt of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and would have us by <hi>ſubſtantia,</hi> under <hi>Subjectum Odoris</hi>) ſtroke in with them and reſolved thus; that which exhaleth from the bodies of things is the ſubſtance of an Odor. On the contrary, <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and all his tribe determine an intentionall, and no ſubſtantiall Emiſſion;<note place="margin">Odores non ſunt ſubſtantiae.</note> and that onely the bare image exhaling from the odorate body, is delated unto, and apprehended by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan of ſmelling. And in truth this latter latter opinion deſerves prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, provided wee admit it with modeſt Caution and diſcreet limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: although the former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes ſomething of reaſon, and but in part deviates from the tract of truth.</p>
               <p>For firſt, the magick of no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments muſt ſeduce us to admit, that Odors are corporeall ſubſtances, <hi>Senſus enim ſubſtantias non percipiunt, ſed tantum earum accidentia;</hi> and wee have already demonſtrated, that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170136:81"/>no ſenſe is actuated into ſenſation, by the reall or materiall, but by the ſpirituall or intentionall quality of the object. Wherefore we ſhall be unreaſonably partiall to deny the ſame to the ſmell; and muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that nothing corporeall, but onely the ſpecies, by <hi>Aporrhoia's</hi> ſtreaming from the odorate body, doth invade the Organ of ſmelling. And on the other ſide, the infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of no Academick can be ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as not to acknowledge, that there is an Effluvium or exhalation from the odorate object, diffuſed into, and tranſported through the Aer; for quotidian experience learns us, that odorate exhalations extend their ſubtile Energy, not onely to the production of divers affections in the brain, proportionate to their own variety and vehemence; to the comfort or affliction of it, by the communication of their own exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in firſt or ſecond, or formall frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or emnity in third and occult qualities, as the Oracle of <hi>Cous</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>Aphor.</hi> 28. Sect. 5. <hi>Odoramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170136:82"/>ſuffitus muliebria educit, &amp; ad alia plerumque utilis eſſet, niſi capitis gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem inferret;</hi> But even to the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vellication and roſion of the noſtrills, eyes, and the tender parts of the face. And again, we obſerve moſt perfumed bodies in tract of time, to fall into minoration of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and ſubſtantiall contabeſcence; and the Odor to continue vigorous in the Aer; a long time after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move of the body, from which it was effluxed. All which are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſto's ſufficient to aſcertain us, that from odorate bodies there doth aſcend a certain corporeall exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, carrying with it the faoulty of Calefaction, Frigefaction, exiccati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, humectation, and other efficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which no Philoſophy can expect from the naked immateriall ſpecies or repreſentative forms of odors: &amp; therfore we willingly ſubſcribe thus much, that from moſt odorables there doth an odorate vapour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale, and that this exhalation is corporeall: but yet, that there is preſumed and required a ſpirituall
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170136:82"/>or intentional image of this odor, to the act of the ſenſe or ſmel of it, is our aſſeveration, and we hope the ſenſe of Truth.</p>
               <p>But whether there be required a concurrence of both? or whether the ſpecies of an Odor,<note place="margin">An ſpecies odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſemper vapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris vehiculo indigeat?</note> which is only and properly the object of ſmel, be alway in conjunction with ſome corporeal ſubject or vapor, without whoſe aſſociation, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be delated to the ſenſorium? is yet in diſpute, and indeed the Axis on which the weight of the whole controverſy is moved. We are ſatisfyed that the coadjutancy of a vapour is not <hi>ſemper, in omnibus et ſingulis,</hi> neceſſary: that this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or exahalation evaporated from the object, does not alway accompany the Odor to the Noſtrials; yea that frequently the object emits no corporeall effluvium at all, and that the ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is very often excited by ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall qualities, or the ſpecies only of an odor, expired from the odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate body, and arriving at the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170136:83"/>For whoever grants this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halation to be alway concomitant to the Odor, as the vehicle or tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſporter of it; muſt infer an alogy not a little derogatory to the great attribute of God, his wiſdome, that is, mutilate the whole fifth daies work, rob all the Citizens of the Ocean of one ſenſe, which by the charter of their Creation, they ſtand poſſeſſed of, and ſubvert the experiment of Anglers, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume their baits.<note place="margin">Boeoti apud An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquos ſtolidita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis et ſtupidita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis nomine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lè audierunt, ut innuit. Horat. in Epiſt. Boeotum incraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, jurares aere natum.</note> For ſince the Soul of an Odor conſiſts <hi>in Sicco à calore elaborato,</hi> and all exhalations by natural propenſity aſcend to unite with the congenerous element of Fire, how much a Boeotian is that headpiece, that can conceive they ſhift their eſſence, and deſcends to the earth in the bottom of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? or when therer arrived, that they can conſerve the integrity of their nature, ſince all odorate bodies no ſooner meet with humectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but they bid adieu to their odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable endowments. Moreover, whence came ſo large and diutur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170136:83"/>an effluvium, which ſerves to qualifie a waſt quantity of Aer, be maintained? Aſſuredly, if the odorate bodies, which are frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of very ſmall bulk, were wholly at once reſolved into vapors, they would not ſuffice to the expletion or tincture of halfe that ſpatious room, which the odors poſſeſſe And 'tis no rarity to obſerve per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes of minute bodies, a long time to maintain the prodigal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of odors, without a maraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus of ſubſtance, or minoration of gravity.</p>
               <p>Our hopes tell us we ſhall offend but venially,<note place="margin">A digreſſion.</note> though we here make a ſhort excurſion on the nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of that queſtion, <hi>An odores nutriendi vim babeant,</hi> whether o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors are endowed with the power of nutrition? For ſince the aliment of a body ought to be corporeall, <hi>&amp; ex iiſdem nutriamur, ex quibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamus;</hi> the materialls of our nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, muſt be congenerous to thoſe of our generation; but odors are but ſimple qualities, and homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170136:84"/>to but one ingredient in our compoſition: we may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that odors can be no pabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum or aliment proper for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation of compound and ſolid bodies; and willingly reſign ſuch aerial paſture to the aſtomy or people without mouths, mentioned by <hi>Pliny,</hi> and after him by our countryman, Sr. <hi>John Mandevil,</hi> (who was very unfortunate in his travails never to viſit <hi>Anticyra</hi>) or to the ofspring of the weſtern wind, the Spaniſh Jennets: and muſt receive what is obſerved in the refocillation or refection of the ſick, either in ſuddain Lypothymies, or Hectick languors, from gratefull and fragrant Odors; and recorded of dying <hi>Democritus,</hi> that with the ſmel of hort bread only, he maintained a three daies ſiege againſt death, to be meant not of the odors, but odorate vapors exhaling from the bread, and other odorables. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is that a true and reall nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is made by the appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition only of an analogous ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170136:84"/>but in propriety of language, a recreation, or refocillation only of the Spirits.</p>
               <p>Concerning the inſtrument of ſmelling, in a licentious acception,<note place="margin">Odoratus Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</note> all men agree upon the Noſe; but in a more ſatisfactory and ſevere, the beſt and moſt Phyſicians have determined, that the two mamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary proceſſes of the brain, are the principall ſenſorium.</p>
               <p>The Noſe is by Anatomie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed into the (1.) External,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Naſus euter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> and (2.) Internal: The External (to omit the parts of it) is in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Nature, inſervient to a manifold uſe: (1.) to the delation of the Aer both into the brain, for the generation of Animal; and lungs, for the material of the vitall ſpirits: (2.) to the delation of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors up to the Papillary protube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of the brain; hence thoſe who have ſuffered amputation of their Noſes, fall inevitably into an utter aboliſhment, or great deprav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their ſmell: (3.) to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuation of the pituitous excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170136:85"/>of the brain: (4.) to aſſiſt the vocall organs in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> formation and melodious articulation of the voice: (5.) to be the beauty and amiable decor of the face: and this certainly was conſidererd by that white aſſembly of Saxon Virgins,<note place="margin">Hinc Virgil. Deiphobi naſi diſſectionem vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat vulnus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſtum. Lib. <hi>6</hi> Aeneid.</note> (whoſe memory ſmells ſweetly in our Engliſh Chronicle) who, to conſerve their conſecrated chaſtity inviolate and unſullied by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent luſt of the inſulting Danes, gladly embraced the amputation of their noſes: taking for granted that deformity was the beſt Antidote againſt a rape, and the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity the want of a noſe.</p>
               <p>The internal noſe conſiſts of two parts only (1.) the <hi>Os</hi> Ethmoides,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Naſus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briforme, or ſpongy bone: (2.) the Mammillary Proceſſes of the brain.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Os Ethmoides</note> The ſpongy bone is the Velamen or muniment of the two mammillary productions, drilled full of ſlender holes or ſpongioſities, through which the inſpired Aer is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately conveyed to the brain, and in which the Aer qualified with
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170136:85"/>Odors, undergoes a praerequiſite alteration and preparation, before it be preſented to the prime Organ of ſmelling, which are two long, white, nervous,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Proceſſus mammilares princeps odora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus organum.</note> productions of the brain, ſituate within in cavity of the ſcul, inveſted, as al other Nerves are, with a craſſe, and thin mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane, and derived to the baſis of the noſe.</p>
               <p>This is a doctrine contemporanie to our reverend Tutor <hi>Hippocrates</hi> deliver'd <hi>Lib.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> thus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The braine doth ſmell the oder of dry things, attracting the ſame toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Aer, through cartila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineous or griſly pipes that are dry: ſupported by <hi>Galen. lib. de Odorat. Organo.</hi> 8. <hi>de uſu Part.</hi> and 1. <hi>de Sympt. Caus.</hi> and is demonſtrable by two irrefragable arguments uſed by <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius</hi> thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> That part is to be accounted the principall and precipuous <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which hath a pecular ſubſtance,figure, and compoſition, witneſſe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170136:86"/>the Aphoriſm of <hi>Galen.</hi> 6. <hi>de Placit. Hippocr. &amp; Platon;</hi> but the mammil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary protuberancies of the brain, amongſt all parts of the noſe, have obtained a peculiar nature, figure, and compoſition, to be found in no other part; but the bones, Cartila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and membranes are in all parts alike: wherefore the principall cauſe of this action of ſmelling is to be aſcribed to the Mammillary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> 
               </p>
               <p>There is no part in the noſe alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by odors, but theſe proceſſes being full of ſpirits, do with facility receive the ſpecies of odors, and being conſubſtantiall to the Nerves, have a notion of that quality they receive.</p>
               <p>The Medium conducible to Odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is Aer and Water,<note place="margin">Medium Odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus.</note> yet neither according to eſence, but qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification and impraegnation. That the Aer infected with an odorate tincture is a medium, hath ever been a truth ratified beyond the dubitation of Pyrrhonian infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. That the water is endowed with
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170136:86"/>the like capacity, and perodorable faculty, we may with <hi>Ariſtotle Lib. de Hiſt Animal.</hi> 4, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. argue from the vulgar experiment of betraying Fiſh with perfumed baites.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the Taſt.</head>
               <p>THe irregular ſophiſtry of ſome, from a circumſtantial affinity concluding an eſſential identity, &amp; from a too ſtrict expoſition of that looſer line of <hi>Ariſtotle, Lib. de ſens. &amp; ſenſili. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Guſtus eſt quoddam genus Tactus,</hi> hath not only ſtarted that Zetema or doubt <hi>An Guſtus ſit idem ſenſus cum potentia, quae qualitates tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibiles percipit?</hi> But with pertinacity maintained the affirmative, and confounded this ſenſe with the Touch. But as the inference is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, ſo is the interpretation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, rendring in a rigid and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſenſe, what was intended in a
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170136:87"/>conditionall, and delivered in terms of ſome latitude. For though at firſt bluſh, the words ſeem to prove that the Touch is the genus and the Taſt but the ſpecies or ſubdiviſion of it: yet to him, that ſhall with ſeverer eyes pry into the deuteroſcopy and medullary intention of them, will it manifeſtly appear that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> meant no more then to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Gognation and ſimilitude betwixt theſe two Senſes. For had the Contents of his thoughts been, that the Taſt and Touch were not in ſpecie different, in probability he would never have ſaid, <hi>Guſtus eſt tactus quidam,</hi> but have ſpared that conditionall particle, and in poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and down right termes have ſaid <hi>Guſtus eſt tactus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither can it become our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to wonder why <hi>Ariſiotle</hi> ſpeaks thus of this ſenſe onely, and not of any other; ſince ſo large an Analogy and reſemblance can be made out, betwixt no two ſenſes, as betwixt this and the Touch; for in both there can bee no comprehenſion,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170136:87"/>without the immediate application of the object on the <hi>Senſorium,</hi> and the contiguity of their extremities: and Guſtable Qualities, in regard of corporeity, materiality, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, ſo fitly correſpond with Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, that wee may ſafely avouch that ſentence of <hi>Ariſtotle, Guſtabile eſt quoddam tangibile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore we muſt acknowledge the Taſt a peculiar Senſe, declaring its dependency on, and diſtinction from the Touch, both <hi>Objecto</hi> and <hi>Organo;</hi> For the object of one is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tangible, of the other <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Guſtable: and the Touch conſerving its integrity and vigor in the tongue, the Taſt may be aboliſhed or depraved: <hi>&amp; ubicunque eſt Tactus, ibi non etiam eſt Guſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is generally defined to bee one of the five externall ſenſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Definitio.</note> whereby wee diſcerne the difference of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours.</p>
               <p>The proper and approximate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Taſting is the Tongue;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Organon.</note> and in particular (not the inveſting Tunicle as <hi>Galen,</hi> and after him <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſius</hi>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:170136:88"/>opinioned,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ineſt. pars ſentiens ſaporem lingua Ariſt. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Hiſtor. Anim.</note> nor the guſtatory nerve expanſed into the inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as ſome conceive by traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from <hi>Columbus</hi>) the pulpe or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous ſubſtance of it, which being of a peculiar and unparralelled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, ſoft, lax, rare and ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, doth imbibe the ſapours, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in their own liquid principles and conſervatories, and impregnated by the ſlaver or ſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val humidity of the mouth.</p>
               <p>External medium there is none;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Medium.</note> for the guſtatory Faculty is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited into the act of comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the diſtantiall, but contigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous poſition, and immediate admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſapid object to the Organ; but the internal medium is the porous pellicle, or ſpongy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegument of the Tongue, aſſiſted by the concurrence, and coefficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the ſpittle, or ſalival exuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it: For this humidity is natures menſtruum, ordained for the maceration, extraction, and impraegnation of ſapors, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paſſed the corrective or auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170136:88"/>operation, of this liquid me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, are through the incontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities, or interſtitiall diviſions of the obducted Membrane, ſoaked into the pulpous ſubſtance of the Tongue, and therein perfected into guſtation. <hi>Vtenim Color objectum viſus eſt, &amp; tamen ſine lumine videri non poteſt: ita ſapor objectum gustus eſt, qui etiam non guſtatur ſine humido, quod eſt veluti actus medij,</hi> was the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The object of the taſt is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Objectum.</note> a Sapour; this is a poſition, whoſe certitude is erected on no meaner foundations then the infallible, and ſcientifick doctrine of our ſenſe, (whoſe information in its own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per buſineſſe, is thought ſuperior to the incroachment of deluſion, and carries authority ſufficient to convert, or ſilence contradiction) and the aggregated affirmation of all Authors, whoſe judgments ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour any thing of reaſon: But what the nature and original of a ſapour is, hath empuzled the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries, and retired from the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170136:89"/>knowledge of thoſe antient wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, <hi>Empedocles, Democritus, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cippus, Anaxagoras, Galen, Ariflotle,</hi> and all ſucceeding Philoſophers; who had not with more then one eye looked into the Arcana of Chymiſtry, and whoſe caecutiency had miſſed the illumination of a Spagyrick Collyrium.</p>
               <p>For though <hi>Galen</hi> and the Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pateticks hunt a ſapour from Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">A digreſſion concerning Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors and their cauſes.</note> and the determinate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperation of their firſt qualities, thus. There is no elemental or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneous body qualified with a ſapour, which is properly an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of compound materialls, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring to its production the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drome, and ſyncriticall union of three principles, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) Terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſiccity, (2.) Aqueous humidity, (3.) Heat, the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ingredient, which carries the maſculine efficiency in operations naturall; for water, in the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of its primitive conſtitution, being inſipid, if percolated through <hi>ſiccum terreſtre,</hi> acquireth a ſapidity
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170136:89"/>proportionate to the intenſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs aduſtion of the materiall diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into concorporation, as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve in fountains, which contract to their ſtreams the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſapors of thoſe ſundry veins of earth, through whoſe ſtraits they have ſteered in their ſubterraneous voyages; and in a lixivium or lie, which admits the amaritude, or ſalſedo; diſcernable in the taſt of it, from its tranſcolation through aſhes: yet the eſſence of a ſapour conſiſts more in <hi>Humido,</hi> then <hi>Sicco,</hi> and is a qualitie affecting the Taſt,<note place="margin">Saporis defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> owing its production to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtion of an aqueous Humidum, with a terreſtrious ſiccum, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound bodies. But ſince the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperature is various, and the Aqueous Humidum united with the earthy Siccium (which is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of ſapors) hath its conſiſtence participating ſometimes of craſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or thickneſſe, and ſometimes of tenuity or thinneſſe; and the Heat (which is the active efficient) varies its activity, according to the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170136:90"/>graduality of intention or remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hence do thoſe various and different kinds of ſapors derive their Original.</p>
               <p>And though Phyſicians on the tradition of theſe principles found the invention of remedies, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect rules for the inveſtigation of the manifeſt faculties of Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by the dignotion of their ſapors;<note place="margin">Fernel Method. Met. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> and to this end conſtitute nine differences or ground diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of ſapors, as they are enumerated by that mouth of the Arabian Oracles, <hi>Eernelius,</hi> thus.</p>
               <p>A ſharp or keen ſapor is that which affects the mouth and tongue with an acrimony,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Acer.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, and calefaction; this is conſpicious in Pepper, Pellitory, Euphorbium, &amp;c. It is ſuſcitated from a thin, dry, and hot matter; nor can it ſubſiſt in a ſubject of any other conſtitution.</p>
               <p>Acide,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Acidus.</note> or ſharp, is that which penetrats and bites the tongue, but without any ſence of heat; ſuch is deprehended in Vinegar, juice of
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170136:90"/>Limons, Citrons, ſome Malaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tones and Quinces: this flowes from a thin, dry matter, or that whoſe innate heat is expired by putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or whoſe Original frigidity is concomitant to tenuity.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Pinguis.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fat, or luſcious, ſollicites the guſto neither with heat nor acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, but furres or daubs the mouth with an unctuous lentor or viſcidity; ſuch is chiefly diſcerned in Oyles, either ſimple, or amyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daline, in butter, &amp; fat, which hath no rancidity, either acquired by antiquity, or originary and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; ſuch as the fat of Lions and Wolves; in mucilaginous plants, as Althaea, &amp;c. This hath its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction from a thin, aeriall matter, temperate in heat and cold.</p>
               <p>A ſalt ſapor doth not very much calefy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Salſus.</note> but by a ſharp ſiccity bite the tongue: this is manifeſt chiefly in ſalt and Nitre; but more obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the herb Crithmum, or ſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier: it ſubſiſts in a matter whoſe ingredients heat and ſiccity are equall. For in water (which is not
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170136:91"/>exquiſitely ſimple) the externall heat in duration of time, torrefying and exiccating thoſe particles or atomicall portions of Earth, which are incorporated with it, induceth a ſaltneſſe and brackiſhneſſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible by the taſt. There is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſalt ſapor produced by Chymiſtry, out of the moſt drie and earthy matter, which the extream and moſt intenſe activity of fire hath torrefied to Cinefaction. And there is no compound body <hi>in rerum natura,</hi> from which a Chymiſt may not extract the Calx and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſalt, diſcernable by the taſt, as from Soot, Tartar, Nitre, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Auſtere doth both mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately bind,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Auſterus.</note> and with a certain aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity or roughneſſe coarctate the parts of the tongue; and hence, in ſome meaſure dry and refrigerate: this is properly called <hi>Crudus ſapor,</hi> and is peculiar to all fruits during their immaturity, as all obſerve in the juice of unripe Grapes, Apples, Pears, Medlars, and alſo Purſellane: it conſiſts in a matter moderately
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170136:91"/>participating earth and water, ſubject to the dominion and exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancy of cold.</p>
               <p>The ſweet ſapor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6.</hi> Dulcis:</note> with ſuavity and jucundity delights the ſenſe, and is not offenſive by the uneven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or ſurpluſage of any qualitie: ſuch is conſpicuous in Sugar, Hony, Liquoriſh, Polypody, Jujubes, and moſt fruits after maturity, and in moſt Lenitive Medicines.</p>
               <p>The Bitter is antagoniſt to the ſweet Sapor, is unpleaſant and offenſive, and doth, as it were,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>7.</hi> Amayus.</note> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade and divell the ſenſe. This no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably diſcovers it ſelf in Alöes, wormwood, the leſſer Centaury and Colocynthis, by whoſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the others are eaſily diſcovered. The matter of it is craſs and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene, torrified and exiccated by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Calidity: and hence <hi>omne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum eſt calidum &amp; ſiccum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſowre borders upon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere or pontick ſapor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>8.</hi> Acerbus:</note> but is far more ungratefull to the ſenſe, doth conſtringe &amp; exaſperate all parts of the mouth, and for this reaſon more
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170136:92"/>dry and cool: prodigally percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is in Pomegranate rindes, Galls, Sumach, Cypreſſe nuts, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chornes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it dwells in a compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion totally terrene and dry; whoſe languid heat is ſubdued to inactivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the conqueſt of its cold ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, confed erate with ſiccity.</p>
               <p>The inſipid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>9.</hi> Inſipidus.</note> fatuous, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is not in the rigor of language, a Sapor, but the privation of it, and doth ſtrike the ſenſe with no manifeſt quality. To this are referred, all the ſpecies of bread-Corn, Gourds, Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trull, Cucumbers, &amp;c. Though theſe are materially craſs, yet not abſolutely earthly, dry, and aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, but daſhed with a portion of humidity, which notwithſtanding is not exquiſitely permixed with ſiccity, by the power of heat. And ſince neither the cold is potentiall in any conſiderable exceſſe, it of neceſſity comes to paſſe, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Sapor can be judged of by the Guſto, nor any quality or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faculty inveſtigated by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility of the effects.</p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:170136:92"/>
               <p>We ſay,<note place="margin">Scaliger. Lib. de plantis, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae qualitates penè ab omniòus exiſtimatae ſunt ſaporum cauſa: tametſi nobis aliter videtur: Nam ſi ſapor à calore fit, ergo calidum elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum primo &amp; per ſe ſapidum eoeiſtet; Quid quòd multa ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lida miſta inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pida. Quod ſi quis dicat ex <hi>4</hi> qualitatum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratione conſici ſaporem; reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat, an in ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento quopiam, qua elementum eſt, ſapor inſit? Non ſane eſt. Coeterum, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madmodum ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vita prodit ab e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementis neque riſus, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, neque intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio, ne que crementum, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> motus volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, ſed à for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis aliis quam elementaribus; ita ſapor quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </note> though the endeavours of moſt have ſteered this courſe, and thus attempted the deduction of ſapors from primitive qualities: yet have they rowled the ſtone in vain: and had not the light of the Chymiſts Fire relieved our benight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed enquiries, they had yet been groping in the obſcurity of error. For wee ſee good reaſon to be of <hi>Scaligers</hi> opinion, that wee may as ſafely deduce life, laughter, ſenſe, intellection, increment and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary motion (actions flowing from Forms more noble and divine) from Elements, as Sapors from their firſt qualities. VVherefore we conclude it more honorable and ſatisfactory to adhaere to the laudable doctrine of Chymiſts, who refer Sapor unto Salt; <hi>Sal enim eſt primum ſapidum &amp; guſtabile, &amp; omnia quae ſaporem habent, eum propter Salem habent. Ubicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim ſapor deprehenditur, ibi ſal est: &amp; ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ſal, ibi ſapor. Sennert. de Conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chymicorum cum Galenicis</hi> cap. 11. wee direct the unſatisfied to that
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170136:93"/>judicious treatiſe of <hi>L. Grillus de de ſapore amaro &amp; dulci.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the Touch.</head>
               <p>THis is that fertile ſenſe, to whoſe delicate invitement we owe our Generation; for had not the wiſdom of providence in her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of immortality, endued the Organs official to the recruit and rejuveneſcence of mankind, with a moſt exquiſite ſenſe of <hi>Touching,</hi> and annexed a pleaſant titillation, or luſtful fury, which tranſports man beyond the ſeverity of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and bewitcheth him to the actions of carnalitie; the Deluge had been ſpared,<note n="*" place="margin">Mare Anton. de ſeipſo. Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Num. <hi>10</hi> tum Coitus, inteſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni parvi affricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o, mucique ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretio, non ſine Convulſione. Ita vertit Meric. Caſaubon.</note> for the firſt age had ſeen the world depopulated, and been the laſt age; and humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had been loſt in the Grave, aſwell as innocence in the fall of our firſt Parents. <hi>Quis enim, per Deum immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talem, concubitum rem adeò faedam ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitaret, amplexaretur; ei indulgeret?
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170136:93"/>Quo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ultu divinum illud Animal ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num rationis et conſilii, quem vocamus hominem, obſcaenas mulierum partes, tot ſordibus inquinatas attrectaret, niſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credibili voluptatis oeſtro percita eſſent Genitalia?</hi> and let us but abate the temptation of this ſenſe, and the libidinous charmes of it, preambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to the act of congreſſion, we ſhall ſoon diſcover that ſo magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a delight of ſenſuality to be no other, then what that noble Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> deſined it <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But the attrition of an ordinary baſe intrall, and the excretion of a little ſnivell, with a certain kind of convulſion, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> deſcribes it.</p>
               <p>This that friend that conſerves us in our firſt life, which we ſpend in the dark priſon of the Womb; uſhers us into this, which our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>providence trifles away on the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perinductions of ſin, and never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes us untill our tranſlation into the future. For when all our other unconſtant ſenſes periſh, or are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170136:94"/>ſmall pertubations of the mind ſuſpended, and leave us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarded, and proſtituted unto the cold embraces of death, this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and unſeparable <hi>Achates</hi> doth attend us unto that moment, which ſhall determine our mortality.<note place="margin">Ariſt. de An. L. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> Text. <hi>67.</hi>
                  </note> Hence <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> drew that progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, that if any creature be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of this ſenſe of. <hi>Touching,</hi> death will of neceſſity enſue: For neither is it poſſible (ſaith he) that any creature ſhould want this ſenſe; neither to the being of a creature is it of neceſſity that he have any ſenſe beſides this.</p>
               <p>In brief, this is that perſwaſive ſenſe, on whoſe teſtimony, the warie Apoſtle choſe to part with his infidelity, and to conclude the preſence of his revived Lord: that painful tender ſenſe, on the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and victory of whoſe torments, the glorious Souls of Martyrs have aſcended to the conſummation of their faith. That virtuall and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinal ſenſe, by which the great Phyſician of the world was pleaſed
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170136:94"/>to reſtore ſight to the blind, ſtrength and activity to the lame, hearing to the deaf, to extinguiſh the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Peters</hi> Mother-law, ſtop the inveterate iſſue of his Haemorrhoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal Patient, unlock the gates of death, and reduce the Widowes Son from the total privation, back to the perfect habit of life.</p>
               <p>Concerning this ſenſe, there are no mean controverſies among Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, and the firſt enquirie is, <hi>An tactus ſit unus numero ſenſus?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An tactus unus numero ſenſus ſit.</note> Whether there be only one ſingle power of touching (as there is one faculty of ſeeing, a ſecond of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, a third of ſmelling, a fourth of taſting) or many diſtinct powers? <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> moves this query. <hi>Lib. de Anima, cap.</hi> 2. and ſubjoynes this reaſon of his dubitation, <hi>Vnus ſenſus eſt unius primae contrarietatis, &amp;c.</hi> One ſingle ſenſe hath but one proper object, to which all, that it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, may be referred: But the touch ſeemes not to have one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon object, but many; for it judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hot and cold, dry and moiſt,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170136:95"/>heavy and light, hard and ſoft, rough and ſmooth, thick and thin, &amp;c. which are not reducible to any one common Genus; and the ſame reaſon, according to which they are qualified for the percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the touch. And by the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of this <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> the faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of ſome, who were far on their journey toward <hi>Athens,</hi> hath been ſeduced ſo wide off the tract of truth, as to fall upon the abſurd belief, <hi>Plures eſſe Tactus,</hi> that there is a plurality of touching Faculties; and of theſe ſome make two, one for the diſcernment of calidity and frigidity, another for the dignotion of humidity and ſiccity; others ſuperadd a third, for the percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of gravity and levity; a third ſect determines, that there are as many diſtinct powers of touching as there are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> differences and contrarieties of tangibles: a fourth hath yet multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied their number, and ſuperad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed others, to the ſenſation of pain and pleaſure, delectation, venery, hunger and thirſt.</p>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:170136:95"/>
               <p>On the contrary, many conclude on the ſingularity of the touch, which although it comprehend objects in number, numerous, and in nature, various and repugnant, yet doth apprehend them all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one common reaſon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate qualification: after the ſame manner that the ſight diſcerns white, black, red, yellow, green, and all <hi>ſub communi colori, coloris ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although we confeſſe our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment below the deciſion of this high diſpute, and that many great Clerks have determined of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but the immpoſſibility of its determination; yet probability in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites us to this latter opinion: <hi>unam eſſe tangendi potentiam.</hi> For although there be a certain, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all immutation in the Organ, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambulous to Taction; and this alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is various and different, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the variety and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of tangibles; yet from this the unity of the Touch is not aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, but only from the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170136:96"/>alteration, ſince it is proper to every ſenſe to receive, not the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall, but intentionall formes of its proper object. And this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall alteration, which is the ſame in all the contrarieties of the tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible objects, conſtitutes one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall ſenſe, otherwaies we may find no leſſe varietie in any of the other ſenſes. Neither ſhall we need to grant a plurality of Touches for pain and pleaſure, ſince pain and pleaſure are not perceived and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by the Touch, but the objects of thoſe paſſions.</p>
               <p>The other greyheaded conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (devolved from great antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the preſent,<note place="margin">Organum tactus</note> and not unlikely to deſcend to the bottom of future times) is concerning the inſtrument of this ſenſe; ſome concluding for the Fleſh, others the Skin, and moſt the Nerves: how lame and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the integrity of truth each of theſe opinions is, our ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding lines will attempt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.<note place="margin">Adaequatum eſt Membrane.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Since every ſenſe hath its pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170136:96"/>Organ, without which the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie muſt remain uſeleſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active: and this Organ is, by the provident law of conſtitution and praediſpoſition, ſubject to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or affection, which the object ſhall impoſe or impreſſe on it; and that part is to be accounted the Organ, which is manifestly affected, and altered by the object; we ſuppoſe the inducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good, if applyed to the touch, that in all members which diſcern tactile qualities, there is the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of touching; and that part which in every place of the body, is affected and changed by tactile qualities, is the Organ of touching. And ſince the touch reſides in no part which is not furniſhed with a membrane, and <hi>ècontra,</hi> whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any membrane is, there is the ſenſe of touching alſo; we conclude, that the Heart Membranes are the true, prime, and adaequate Organs of the Touch, and that all parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their ſenſibilitie from them.</p>
               <p>Some have endeavoured the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170136:97"/>of this opinion, but with vain and inconſiderable objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Non Caro.</note> for what they urge; that the Fleſh is endowed with the ſenſe of feeling, is manifeſtly falſe. For the Fleſh feels not <hi>per ſe,</hi> or by any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible power inhaerent to it ſelfe, but as it is furniſhed with Nervous, or Membranous Fibres, which are beſtowed on the ſubſtance of the Muſcles: But the Fleſh of the viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cera, and glandules, whoſe ſubſtance is unprovided of Fibres, is wholly devoid of ſenſibility.</p>
               <p>And although <hi>Galen</hi> teach us,<note place="margin">Nee Necuus.</note> 
                  <hi>Lib. de placit.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that every part furniſhed with a Nerve, enjoys the ſenſe of feeling; yet are we to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Axiom tru o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in a qualified ſenſe, that is <hi>quatenus ipſi nervi mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branoſi ſunt;</hi> as the nerves themſelves are membranous, and diſſeminate their fibrous ſurcles and capillary productions on the parts. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if we conſider the Nerves in <hi>ſenſu diviſo,</hi> in the naked ſimplicitie of their own natures, as they are
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170136:97"/>ſtrictly and properly nerves, they are not the proper inſtrument of touching, but Canales or conduits inſervient to the diſtribution and tranſvection of the Animall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits into all parts of the body, in which reſpect they are officiall to the touch no more, then to the reſt of the ſenſes. But that qualification and endowment of ſenſibility they poſſeſſe, they borrow from the membranes, wherewith they are inveſted; as ordinary obſervation of wounds of the Nerves, eſpecially the greater ones, wil inform us; for the meduallary ſubſtance may be handled and drawn forth of the wound, without any pain at all; but if the coat or membrane be but touched, moſt exquiſite and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibletorments immediately enſue.</p>
               <p>Concerning the skin,<note place="margin">Cutis eſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum tactus, praecipuum, ſed non adaequatum.</note> we grant it to be the common integument of the body, whoſe principal and publick action is <hi>eſse tactus inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum &amp; ad ſubjectarum partium tutelam,</hi> to be the inſtrument of Touching, and diſcern external
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170136:98"/>injurious inſtruments that invade the body; and we beleeve that <hi>Galen</hi> ſaid very truely, <hi>Cutem, maxime quae eſt in manu, omnium ſenſibilium normam eſse, &amp; tactus instrumentum, pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimo Animali proprium, qua, ut com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni inſtrumento, adres tangendas &amp; apprehendendas, omnium qualitatum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibilium differentiae melius quam ulla alia corporis parte, dignoſcuntur:</hi> Yet we cannot concede it to be <hi>unicum et ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequatum tactus Organum,</hi> the only and adaequate inſtrument of touching; but ſince other parts could not want this ſenſe for the avoidance of deſtructive and noxious objects, nature hath been far more bountifull, and diffuſed it into the moſt retired parts; and for this reaſon the Membranes are diſperſed through all the body, and by their mediation the ſenſe of touching, which in many of the internal parts is moſt exquiſite and acute.</p>
               <p>The collection of all is, that the praecipuous Organ of the touch, is
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:170136:98"/>the skin, chiefly that part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the hands are lined, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtined to the common apprehenſion of all things tangible: but the adae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate, are the membranes; by the benefit whereof, all other parts (the skin excepted) obtain the ſenſe of Feeling.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
